<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Beverly Crest</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <!-- we could also use type = entry or type=chapter-->
                
                <head>Beverly Crest</head>
                <byline>Primary Author: Janice L. Reiff</byline>
                <figure>
                    <graphic url="http://emcaulay.bol.ucla.edu/sunset/images/beverly_crest_intro.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                
                <p>For a profile of the Beverly Crest today, 
                    see the <title>Los Angeles Times’</title> Mapping L.A. project at 
                    http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/beverly-crest/.
                </p>
                
                <div type="bus_notes">
                    <head>Bus Notes</head>
                    <p>As you might expect for a neighborhood designed from the outset to ensure privacy, there is relatively little to see from the bus in the brief stretch of Beverly Crest / Holmby Hills that you will pass through between Beverly Glen Boulevard and the western edges of <placeName>Beverly Hills</placeName>.  This is also (as indicated by the lack of sidewalks) not a walking area.</p>
                </div>
                <!-- closes bus notes div -->
                
                <div type="sunset_notes">
                    <head>Sunset Notes</head>
                    <p>As real estate development west of Beverly Hills expanded in the 1920s, popular agitation increased for an improved road that skirted the foothills of the Santa Monica Mountains.  Beverly Boulevard, as the existing street was known, needed to be improved in places (like the area along <placeName>Beverly Crest</placeName>) and built in others.  In 1926, the people of Los Angeles approved a bond issue to pay for these improvements.  In 1934, Beverly Boulevard assumed the name of the famous Sunset Boulevard to which it connected in <placeName>Beverly Hills</placeName>.</p>
                </div>
                <!-- closes sunset notes div -->
                
                <div type="historical_overview">
                    <head>Historical Overview</head>
                    <p> <placeName>Beverly Crest</placeName>, although designated by the <title>Los Angeles Times</title> as a neighborhood and incorporated into <orgName>Los Angeles City Government</orgName> through the <orgName>Bel-Air-Beverly Crest Neighborhood Council</orgName>, is a neighborhood few who don’t sell real estate or live in the neighborhood would recognize as an LA neighborhood.   That is because the area that makes up <placeName>Beverly Crest</placeName> is composed of areas better known to the public: <placeName>Benedict Canyon</placeName>, <placeName>Beverly Glen</placeName>, <placeName>Coldwater Canyon</placeName>, <placeName>Holmby Hills</placeName>, <placeName>North Beverly Glen</placeName>, the edges of <placeName>Laurel Canyon</placeName>, an unincorporated area in <placeName>Franklin Canyon</placeName>, and the area known as <placeName>Beverly Hills Post Office</placeName> – the part of Los Angeles that shares the famous Beverly Hills 90210 zip code.  </p><p>
                        
                        The section of Beverly Crest that lies closest to Sunset is familiarly known as Holmby Hills, one of three communities (with Bel-Air and Beverly Hills) often identified as Los Angeles’s “Platinum Triangle.”  The evolution of Holmby Hills, which lies both north and south of Sunset, is closely tied to Westwood.  When department store magnate <persName>Arthur Letts, Sr.</persName> purchased the <placeName>Wolfskill Ranch</placeName> (see Westwood), he christened the foothills areas closest to Beverly Hills as Holmby Hills in homage to his British roots and his Holmby House estate in Los Feliz.  That home, with its mansion and elaborate gardens, served as a model for the community he imagined for Holmby Hills.  Although Letts, Sr. never lived in Holmby Hills, most of his family did and it quickly became one of Los Angeles’s most elite neighborhoods.  As the <title>New York Times</title> wrote in a March 4, 1945 article on actor and crooner <persName>Bing Crosby</persName>, who lived at <placeName>594 S. Mapleton Drive</placeName> just east of <placeName>Holmby Park</placeName>, his mansion was located on “one of the seventy Holmby Hills, an expensive tract which stands with its back to Beverly Hills and its nose in the air over Westwood.”
                        <figure>
                            <graphic url="http://emcaulay.bol.ucla.edu/sunset/images/BeverlyCrest_G4364_LA_13_5_JIC_1931_cropped.jpg"></graphic>
                            <p>Excerpt from Janss Investment Corporation map of Westwood and Holmby Hills, c 1931. Available online at <ref target="http://digital2.library.ucla.edu/viewItem.do?ark=21198/zz002c21mb">http://digital2.library.ucla.edu/viewItem.do?ark=21198/zz002c21mb</ref>
                                <!-- To see the whole map, go to www.hypercities.com, click on Launch HyperCities, and select Los Angeles.
                                You will only be able to select the map if the window includes that part of the city.  So zoom out, until you are able to see 1931 Westwood and Holmby as a map choice.  Click it (it will take a moment to become visible) and then negotiate your way to the map.  At this point, you are really using Google Maps so you should have no problem seeing it in detail. -->
                                The map is from the UCLA Charles E. Young Research Library Bruman Map Collection.  
                            </p>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>In 1927, <persName>Arthur Letts, Jr.</persName> built his 14,000 foot mansion Gothic-Tudor style mansion on 5.3 acres of land located at <placeName>10236 Charing Cross Road</placeName>, south of Sunset where Charing Cross touches the edge of the <placeName>Los Angeles Country Club</placeName> on this map.  Thirty-four years and one owner later, <persName>Hugh Hefner</persName> purchased the estate, expanded and updated it, and turned it into the <placeName>Playboy Mansion</placeName>.  Four years earlier, <persName>Harold Janss</persName>, married to <persName>Letts’ daughter Gladys</persName>, had built his 20 room mansion at <placeName>375 N. Carolwood Drive</placeName>, north of Sunset Boulevard, and <persName>his brother and partner, Edwin</persName>, had constructed his mansion set well back from Sunset near the <placeName>corner of Sunset and Carolwood</placeName>.
                        <figure>
                            <graphic url="http://emcaulay.bol.ucla.edu/sunset/images/BeverlyCrest_HolmbyHills.jpg"></graphic>
                            <p>Display ad 91 -- no title. (1925, Apr 26). <title>Los Angeles Times (1923-Current File)</title>, pp. 5-F5. Retrieved from http://search.proquest.com/docview/161829358?accountid=14512
                                
                            </p>
                        </figure></p>
                    
                    
                    <p>The size of these mansions and their privacy from streets like Sunset was typical for the hill areas of the “Platinum Triangle.”  What was distinctive, especially compared to neighboring <placeName>Bel-Air</placeName>, was that its restrictions on who could live there were much less narrowly defined.  Protected from the middle class by the required lot size, from redevelopment for a provision that prohibited any subdividing for 50 years, and by deed covenants (“in perpetuity,” but, in reality, not after the 1948 Supreme Court ruling) from those not of the Caucasian race, Holmby Hills allowed both Jews and movie people.  Movie stars and wealthy entrepreneurs moved there beginning in the 1920s and continue to live there today.  <persName>Michael Jackson</persName> was living in Holmby Hills when he died.  </p>
                    
                    <p>Of special note in Holmby Hills is the campus of <orgName>Harvard-Westlake Middle School</orgName>.  The <orgName>Westlake School for Girls</orgName> moved to Holmby Hills in 1927.  <persName>Jessica Smith Vance</persName> and <persName>Frederica de Laguna</persName> opened the school in 1904 on <placeName>Sixth Street and Alvarado</placeName>, near <placeName>Westlake Park</placeName> (now <placeName>MacArthur Park</placeName>).  After an earlier move, they relocated to Holmby Hills at the suggestion of <persName>Harold Janss</persName>.  He saw the school as one of the anchors for the elite community.  In the 1940s, the <persName>Temple family</persName> assumed ownership and, in the mid-1960s, the school phased out its elementary school classes and reorganized as a non-profit organization.  In 1989, the Board of Trustees of Westlake and of <orgName>Harvard School</orgName>, founded originally in 1900 as a military school for boys, merged.  The Holmby Hills campus houses the Harvard-Westlake Middle School, the High School is on the site of the defunct <orgName>Hollywood Country Club</orgName> on Coldwater Canyon.  Children living in the Beverly Crest area who attend <orgName>LAUSD</orgName> (Los Angeles Unified School District)  schools go to elementary and middle school in Westwood and high school at <orgName>University High School</orgName>.  </p>
                    
                    <p>No longer there, but famous in its day was <orgName>Walt Disney’s Carolwood Pacific Railroad</orgName>.  After <persName>Disney</persName> moved his family to Holmby Hills in 1949.  to an estate north of the Harold Janss home on Carolwood, he built a live steam backyard railroad for him, his children and their friends.  If you have ridden the train at Disneyland, you have experienced some of what the ride was like.</p>
                    
                    <p>Holmby Hills is also home to Los Angeles’ largest home – the manor located at <placeName>594 S. Mapleton Drive</placeName>.  Formerly the home of <persName>Aaron</persName>, <persName>Cindy</persName> (and <persName>Tori</persName>) Spelling, the 52,503 square foot home was sold in 2011 for $85,000,000.  The home was built on the site of the Crosby home mentioned above after it was torn down.  That building had been built originally in 1932 for <persName>Malcom McNaghten</persName>, the president of the <orgName>Broadway Department Store</orgName> and husband to Arthur Letts’ daughter and sister of Harold Janss’ wife.</p>
                    <p>Beverly Crest is part of the <orgName>Bel-Air Beverly Crest Neighborhood Council</orgName>.  These councils were authorized in the 1999 Los Angeles charter to empower residents of neighborhoods to organize stakeholders to serve neighborhood needs.  In the summer of 2012, both the <title>Los Angeles Times</title> and the blog CurbedLA reported that at least one resident of Holmby Hills approached the <orgName>Beverly Hills City Council</orgName> to see if Holmby north of Sunset and east of Beverly Glen might be annexed into that city where it might get better municipal services.</p>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="bibliography">
                    <p>In addition to the individual sources and databases included above, the sources below were particularly useful:  </p>
                    
                    <bibl>Bel Air-Beverly Crest Neighborhood Council.  <ref target="http://babcnc.org">http://babcnc.org/</ref></bibl>
                    
                    <bibl>
                        <author> Brasuell, James. </author> “Holmby Hills Asks Beverly Hills to Take It In, Pave Its Streets.”  CurbedLA (30 July 2012).  <ref target="http://la.curbed.com/archives/2012/07/holmby_hills_asks_beverly_hills_to_take_it_in_pave_its_streets.php">http://la.curbed.com/archives/2012/07/holmby_hills_asks_beverly_hills_to_take_it_in_pave_its_streets.php</ref>.  Accessed on September 20, 2012.</bibl>
                    
                    <bibl>
                    <author>Gross, Michael. </author> <title>Unreal Estate: Money, Ambition, and the Lust for Land in Los Angeles.</title>  New York, NY:  Broadway, 2011.
                    </bibl>
                    
                   
                </div>
                
                <div type="Points_of_Interest">
                    <head>On the bus...</head>
                    <p>Because Holmby Hills was designed to protect the privacy of its residents, there is relatively little to see on the very short bus ride between Westwood and Beverly Hills.  There are, however, several things to note as you go through.</p>
                    
                    <div type="item" n="1">
                        
                        
                        <head> N. Beverly Glen Boulevard and Sunset Boulevard</head>
                        
                        <p>Beverly Glen Boulevard was an important connector between the Janss’ Westwood and Holmby Hills developments and the San Fernando Valley.  Like most similar canyon roads, it also served to channel water from the higher ground to the lower lying areas.   On January 16, 1952, Los Angeles experienced a 3.39 inch rainfall in an especially wet year.  The result was, according the to Los Angeles Times the following day, hundreds of families evacuated from their homes, thousands of cars caught in mud and water above their windows, bridged washed out and dynamited to accommodate the floods, and a least four people died in the worst floods since 1938.  The homes along Beverly Glen and in the narrow streets off the Glen experienced substantial damage. 
                            <figure><graphic url="http://emcaulay.bol.ucla.edu/sunset/images/BeverlyCrest_USC_Flood.jpg"></graphic><p>This photograph taken for the Los Angeles Examiner shows John Shelby riding his bike on Sunset at the Bel-Air gates after the worst of the flood was over.  The sign, which indicates that Oxnard is 42 miles away, gives some sense of Sunset’s role as a major thoroughfare in the years before the freeways..   
                                http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/assetserver/controller/view/EXM-N-9456-089~6
                                http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/search/controller/view/examiner-m8359.html?x=1348179612958
                            </p></figure>
                       
                    </p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="item" n="2">
                        
                        
                        <head>  The gates visible from Sunset at S. Carolwood Drive </head>
                        
                        <p>Behind the gates at 141 S. Carolwood Drive is the former home of Arthur Letts’ widow, Florence.  A later owner of the estate was Joseph W. Drown, longtime owner of the Bel-Air and Ocean House (Santa Monica) hotels.  Subsequent residents included W. M. Keck (after whom the W. M. Keck Foundation is named and founder and president of Superior Oil), actor Tony Curtis, and actress and singer Cher and her husbands, Sonny Bono and Gregg Allman.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="item" n="3">
                        
                        
                        <head> 10086 Sunset Boulevard (on the south side of Sunset at the intersection with N. Carolwood Drive)</head>
                        
                        <p>There is nothing to see here because the address actually never existed.  It is, nonetheless, iconic – the supposed home of actress Norma Desmond in Billy Wilder’s 1950 film Sunset Boulevard.  Set back from the street at 10060 Sunset was the now-demolished home of Edwin Janss and his family. 
                            <figure><graphic url="http://emcaulay.bol.ucla.edu/sunset/images/beverly_crest_film_still_sunset_blvd.jpg"></graphic><p>A still image from the production of <title>Sunset Boulevard</title>. This image is part of the UCLA Library Special Collections, in the Motion Pictures Still collection.</p>
                                <!-- 	The clip from Sunset Boulevard that was at the you tube address was taken down due to copyright infringement. Perhaps we should use the trailer instead: http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=imXKJfmdhGM ? In the meantime, I have put in an image from the Library Special Collections Motion Pictures Stills collection. 
                                original text: Watch the opening sequence of the film on YouTube at http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nQNh_m3YIBc.  Although the mansion used was actually the now demolished Getty Mansion at 641 S. Irving Boulevard near Wilshire.--> </figure>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
