<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Brentwood</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <!-- we could also use type = entry or type=chapter-->
                
                <head>Brentwood</head>
                <byline>Primary Authors: Janice L. Reiff</byline>
        
                
                <p>For a profile of the Pacific Palisades today, 
                    see the Los Angeles Times’ Mapping L.A. project at 
                    http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/brentwood/.
                </p>
                
                <div type="bus_notes">
                    <head>Bus Notes</head>
                    <p>Although you enter and return from Brentwood through a somewhat circuitous route on the bus, once the bus makes it to Sunset, it stays on Sunset.  The jogs from the boulevard represent, as in Westwood, an effort to serve the clusters of population on either side of the 405.  Reflecting ridership, bus stops are farther apart in Brentwood than in Westwood or in communities closer to downtown and there are fewer buses.  For those reasons, be sure to keep the schedule in mind when you get off to explore Brentwood.</p>
                </div>
                <!-- closes bus notes div -->
                
                <div type="sunset_notes">
                    <head>Sunset Notes</head>
                    <p>As you skirt around the Sunset Bridge over the 405, you have a chance to see the newest road work on Sunset Boulevard.  The bridge was in the process of being rebuilt and torn down for many months until it was reopened (to the great relief of those who drive on Sunset everyday) in September 2012.  The rest of Sunset Boulevard shares the history of the development of Beverly Boulevard in the 1920s and its renaming and improving in the 1930s.  Never Brentwood’s “main street,” an appellation better applied to San Vicente Boulevard, Sunset has been a path through the community and a connector to the important connecting streets into the various canyons around which most of Brentwood’s neighborhoods have formed.</p>
                </div>
                <!-- closes sunset notes div -->
                
                <div type="historical_overview">
                    <head>Historical Overview</head>
                    <p>Brentwood’s development is closely linked to that of Santa Monica and the Veteran’s Home.  Part of the Rancho San Vincente y Santa Monica, the land was first granted to the Mexican government in 1828 to Don Francisco Sepulveda. The Tongva people who originally lived there had earlier been moved to the Mission San Gabriel.  Nearly half a century later, in 1872, the Sepulveda family sold most of their holdings to Col. Robert S. Baker, who had amassed substantial wealth during the California Gold Rush.  In 1875, he married one of Los Angeles’ wealthiest widows – Arcadia Bandini de Stearns.  That same year, he sold some two-thirds of his holdings to Nevada Senator John P. Jones and the two sub-divided some of their common holdings along the ocean coast to create the town of Santa Monica.   As the Southern California land boom burst in 1887, Baker deeded most of the rest of his land to his wife.  He and Jones, however, continued their efforts to find ways of making their land holdings more profitable.  The story of their successful effort to capture the Soldiers’ Home for themselves and for Los Angeles appears in the Historical Overview for the Veterans’ Administration. <figure><graphic url=""></graphic><p>Relief shown pictorially.4362 S3194From: U.S. District Court. California, Southern District. Land case 143 SD, page 199; land case map B-1155 (Bancroft Library)  United States. District Court (California : Southern District). Land case. 143, Related Name Indexing Term http://content.cdlib.org/ark:/13030/hb5f59n92k/?query=rancho%20san%20vicente%20y%20santa%20monica&amp;brand=calisphere
                    </p></figure> </p>
                    
                    <p>What became Brentwood is the story of the development of the land between those two anchors – and beyond them north into the Santa Monica Mountains.  The Veterans’ Home was most immediately important.  In 1897, a small settlement grew up to the south of its grounds on land Jones and Baker had originally donated to the Santa Monica and Pacific Railway.  The railway, preferring cash to property, sold the land to R. F. Jones and Robert C. Gillis.  They recruited someone to help with the development and the community that resulted eventually took the name of Sawtelle after William E. Sawtelle, a resident and friend of Gillis.
                        <figure><graphic url=""></graphic><p>"Display Ad 65 -- no Title." Los Angeles Times (1886-1922), May 10, 1905. http://search.proquest.com/docview/164374018?accountid=14512.</p></figure>
                        <figure><graphic url=""></graphic><p>Display Ad 46 -- no Title." Los Angeles Times (1886-1922), Apr 27, 1907. http://search.proquest.com/docview/159085771?accountid=14512.</p></figure>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>
                        In 1905, Gillis expanded his landholdings by buying the Santa Monica Land and Water Company, the firm started by Baker and Jones.  Based in part of the success of Sawtelle, which incorporated as a town in 1906, Gillis established a new settlement near the west gate of the Veterans’ Home – a community he named Westgate.  Westgate Acres, Westgate Gardens, and Westgate Heights followed soon thereafter.  Further west, on 350 acres north of San Vincente Boulevard which was emerging as the major transportation link in the area, the Western Pacific Development Company created Brentwood Park with large lots, wide streets, traffic circles, and the promise of trees.  Among the Company’s investors were William Lynton Brent, president of the Merchants Trust Company Bank, and William S. Vawter, president of the Santa Monica Saving Bank and vice-president of the Merchants’ National Bank of Santa Monica.  By 1910, several locations in what would come to be known as Brentwood were stops on the Pacific Electric Company’s “Balloon Route” that was popular both with those looking for places to live and tourists intrigued by Los Angeles’ diverse neighborhoods and landscapes. 
                        <figure><graphic url=""></graphic><p>Detail from Map of the Los Angeles Pacific Electric Company lines around Los Angeles, 1910
                            USC Digital Library
                            http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/search/controller/view/chs-m13242.html?x=1351431572696
                        </p></figure>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>Although subdividing in the Brentwood area had slowed in the 1907-1912 era, it resumed soon thereafter, fueled by a better real estate market and the promise of water from the Owens River Valley.  Late in 1913, developer James R. H. Wagner (who was also president of the Pasadena Tournament of Roses parade) announced Brentwood Place, located immediately across from what a report in the January 11, 1914, Los Angeles Times described as the “far-famed” Brentwood Park.  The newspaper’s celebration of the new subdivision, almost certainly written by someone in Wagner’s firm, was even more positive.  [Brentwood Place] “is in every sense of the word one of the highest-class subdivisions that has yet been put on the market in Southern California.”  Celebrating the tennis courts built for Brentwood Park, San Vincente (‘one of the most famed, most important and most picturesque boulevards in Southern California”), and the infrastructural amenities, it also pointed to this area’s strong connection to Santa Monica.  In fact, it described the subdivision as being located in one of the most beautiful parts of the “widely-famed Santa Monica, noted as one of the world’s most ideal health and pleasure resorts, and one of its most superb home cities…”  </p>
                    
                    <p>In 1915, a group of developers and residents laid the ground work for still another amenity for Brentwood – a country club.  Among its first officers and board of directors were tennis star T. C. Bundy: well-known Santa Monica civic and business leader and golfer, Thomas McCall; C. L. Bundy, one of the developers of the first Westgate Tract; James R. H. Wagner; Dr. Herman Janss, co-founder of Janss Investment Company; Dr. C. P. Thomas, owner of one of the largest homes in Brentwood Place; Col. L. B. Wood, who oversaw the building of the Pilgrim Club on Catalina Island; W. L. Desnoyers, realtor; and several others.  The location of the Country Club, between San Vincente and Montana, Graetna Green and Burlingame ensured that it would be equally accessible to residents of the City of Santa Monica and to Brentwood, still an unincorporated part of Los Angeles County.<figure><graphic url=""></graphic><p>Adelbert Bartlett, Brentwood Country Club, 1940.
                        Santa Monica Public Library Image Archive.
                        http://digital.smpl.org/cdm4/item_viewer.php?CISOROOT=/smarchive&amp;CISOPTR=1386&amp;CISOBOX=1&amp;REC=2
                    </p></figure></p>
                    
                    <p>The question of whether Brentwood would be part of Los Angeles or Santa Monica came to a vote in 1916 when Westgate – an approximately 48.5 square mile area from the Soldiers’ Home to Pacific Palisades – voted to be annexed to the City of Los Angeles.  The primary reason for annexation was access to the water from the Los Angeles Aqueduct, water that was only available to residents and land in the City of Los Angeles.  Annexation was not, however, without challenges.  Westgate voters first pushed to be a borough of Los Angeles, allowing for a new structure for their relationship with the city.  Unfortunately, however, the proposition that would have allowed New York’s borough structure in Los Angeles lost in the same election.  Another effort for independence depended on whether the Brentwood areas of Westgate could get its water from Santa Monica instead.  That effort also failed.</p>
                    
                    <p>
                        
                        Those close ties with Santa Monica remained.   Perhaps the most visible marker of those ties today is the Brentwood Country Mart, located at Brentwood’s western boundary on 26th Street and San Vincente.  Opened in November 1948, it was designed as a Westside equivalent of the Fairfax Farmers’ Market.  Its shops, retail stalls, and restaurants made it popular.  Within several years, it had become the community center for west Brentwood, North Santa Monica, and, to a lesser extent, the more distant parts of Brentwood that were more likely to do their shopping closer to the area that was earlier known as Westgate further east on San Vincente near Bundy or even, for those living closer to Sunset, to Brentwood Village.  
                      </p>
                    
                    <p>Those emerging “centers” of Brentwood reveal something about the ways in which the neighborhood, now almost synonymous with comfort and wealth in Los Angeles, took form in the middle decades of the twentieth century.   The decline in the housing market that preceded the Great Depression had a significant impact on Brentwood.  One clear indication came in 1928 when the Brentwood Country Club went into foreclosure.  The club, home a decade before to aspiring Westside elites, was purchased by the exiled King Carol of Romania.  He made the golf course public, charging green fees instead of membership fees.  He also transformed the upper floor of the club house into a hotel.  <figure><graphic url=""></graphic><p>"Display Ad 2 -- no Title." Los Angeles Times (1923-Current File), Oct 15, 1947. http://search.proquest.com/docview/165804194?accountid=14512.</p></figure></p>
                    
                    <p>The HOLC document for the former Westlake area – the area south of San Vincente by the 1930s identified as Brentwood Heights – also suggests a community for which the future was less than certain.  Describing an area of tradesmen, skilled workers and a few white collar workers, of 4-5 room bungalows, and of Japanese &amp; Mexicans along the eastern boundary that threatened infiltration, the description of the area was as follows.
                        
                       <quote> Land improved 60% out of a possible 90%. Conveniences are all readily available. This area was subdivided approximately 20 years ago, and developed as a medium priced district. Construction and maintenance are both spotted, but is generally of better quality in the western and northern parts than in balance of area. The new construction is largely in this section and is of much better character than the older improvements, indicating an upward trend. Lots average 50 feet and front foot values range from $16 to $18. Population and improvements are both more or less heterogeneous. The area is assigned a "medial yellow" grade.</quote>
                        
                        The Sunset-Sepulveda area located south of Sunset and west of Sepulveda Boulevard, the pocket then better-known as the Ratteree Tract, received a similar yellow rating.  Although the “authorities” cited could not agree on the best rating for the area because its future direction had yet to be established, the mixed history of the area that had failed to thrive since its platting in 1920 led them to settle on the lower grade.   Both reports, however, pointed to the positive impact FHA loans were having in the neighborhoods.
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>North of San Vincente and west of the Country Club, however, the HOLC ratings were much more positive.  In old Westgate north of San Vincente, the description noted the real development spurred by FHA funding, as well as the racial and land-use restrictions to award it a blue rating, despite the proximity to the Soldiers’ Home.  Brentwood Heights above Sunset, Tigertail Estates, Highland Heights, Mandeville Canyon, and Brentwood Park each received blue of green ratings, noting that the isolation and privacy of the locales were an amenity those living there desired.  The documents also took note of the fact that some from the movie industry had moved into these more elite areas of Brentwood and that these new residents were adding to the appeal of those neighborhoods and driving the prices of land higher.</p>
                    
                    <p>These documents pointed to the direction Brentwood would take in the years after World War II.  The Brentwood Farmers Mart mentioned above confirmed a type of community identity and lifestyle.  So, too, did the efforts of Arthur Edmunds and Edward Zuckerman to re-establish the Brentwood Country Club as a private club.  Local developers, they had witnessed the changing ownership of the club since 1928 and knew that developers were eying the property for a new subdivision.  They, however, were interested in access to a country club that allowed Jewish members.  Although the Hillcrest Country Club which had always admitted Jews was relatively nearby (10000 Pico), its membership rolls were full.  So, the two men launched a successful effort to buy the Brentwood Country Club and open it to members regardless who could pay the entry fee.  Only Crestwood Hills (see below) seemed out of step with other developments in Brentwood.  Its mutual housing model and its initial plan for a racially integrated community stood in sharp contrast to the rest of the larger community that had come to be known as Brentwood.   Still, with its appealing architecture and landscaping, it too fit into what Brentwood had become.</p>
                    
                    <p>Brentwood’s population grew in the last half of the twentieth century as new homes were built further up in the canyons.  It grew in popularity as a place for movie stars and other celebrities to live.  Neighborhood amenities grew, as a drive down San Vincente Boulevard’s lush median strip, formerly home to the street car rails, is now a favorite site for joggers.  Its reputation as a community with rich educational resources, established by its proximity to UCLA and with Mount St. Mary’s construction of a new campus there in 1928 (the Chalon campus), has grown as private schools have flourished there.  The decision to site the Getty Center in the hills of Brentwood confirmed its reputation as a cultural center.
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url=""></graphic>
                        <p>Graduation at Mt. St. Mary’s, 1951
                            Los Angeles Examiner Negative Collection, 1950-61
                            USC Digital Library
                            http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/search/controller/view/examiner-m1810.html?x=1352220366571
                        </p>
                    </figure>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>The decision to locate the Getty Center where it is also reinforced Brentwood’s reputation for exclusivity.  Although the roads between the Sunset Circle neighborhood (north of Sunset, west of the 405) did not connect with the Getty Center, its proximity above Sunset Circle and concerns about potential increased public access led the neighborhood to petition the Los Angeles City Council to let it become a fully gated community.  In 1995, the City Council agreed, making Sunset Circle Los Angeles’ first gated community.  Later, Brentwood Country Estates in Mandeville Canyon was also allowed to become a gated community with residents paying fees to cover the costs associated with that designation.  </p>
                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="bibliography">
                    <p>In addition to the individual sources and databases included above, the sources below were particularly useful:  </p>
                    
                    <bibl> <author> Braun, Stephen.</author> “West Hollywood Adopts Tough Rent Control Law.” <title>Los Angeles Times</title> Los Angeles, Calif., United States, June 28, 1985. http://search.proquest.com/hnplatimes/docview/154242572/abstract?accountid=14512. </bibl>
                   
                   <bibl>
                      <author> Brentwood Country Mart.</author>  History.  Available at http://www.brentwoodcountrymart.com/history/.</bibl><bibl>
                      <author> City of Los Angeles.</author>  Annexation Map.  Available at http://navigatela.lacity.org/common/mapgallery/pdf/annex34x44.pdf.</bibl><bibl>
                      <author> Home Owners Loan Corporation.</author>  Area Description C-64, Brentwood Heights (http://salt.unc.edu/T-RACES/data/la/ad/ad0257.pdf); C-65, Sunset-Sepulveda (http://salt.unc.edu/T-RACES/data/la/ad/ad0258.pdf).  1939.  </bibl><bibl>
                      <author> Strawn, Paul R. </author>"The Mutual Housing Association of Los Angeles, a Case Study in Cooperation." MBA thesis, University of California, Los Angeles, 1951</bibl><bibl>
                      <author> Towne, Robert.</author>  “Brentwood Country Club’s History Is Probably Greek to Marathoners.”  SI Vault (June 25, 1984).  Available at http://sportsillustrated.cnn.com/vault/article/magazine/MAG1122203/2/index.htm.</bibl><bibl>
                       <author>Zollman, Harold and Roger Friedland.</author>  “Broadacre in Brentwood?  The Politics of Architectural Aesthetics.”  In Charles G. Salas and Michael S. Roth (eds),<title> Looking for Los Angeles</title>, 167-210.  Los Angeles: Getty Research Institute, 2010.
                       
                   </bibl>
                   
                </div>
                
                <div type="Points_of_Interest">
                    <div type="item" n="1">
                        
                        
                        <head>  Getty Center of the J. Paul Getty Museum, 1200 Getty Center Drive</head>
                        
                        <p>The Getty Center opened in 1997 as the second campus (the first at the Getty Villa in the Pacific Palisade) of the J. Paul Getty Museum.  The site for the sprawling 24-acre campus surrounded by 600 acres of land targeted to remain in its “natural” state was purchased in 1983.  Sitting at an elevation of approximately 900 feet, the Center when finished quickly became a Westside landmark and, on clear days, provides a stunning view that reaches from the San Bernardino and San Gabriel Mountains to the east, downtown Los Angeles toward the southeast, and the Pacific Ocean on the west.
                    </p>
                        
                        <p>New York architect Richard Meier designed the complex that includes a museum for what the Getty Trust describes as its “pre-20th century European paintings, drawings, illuminated manuscripts, sculpture, and decorative arts and 19th- and 20th- century American and European photographs,” the Getty Research Institute, the Getty Conservation Institute, administrative offices of the Getty Foundation and Trust, and a library, as well as an impressive central garden designed by artist Robert Irwin.</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="itme" n="2">
                        <head>Brentwood School, 100 S Barrington Place and 12001 Sunset Boulevard</head>
                        <p>The Brentwood School’s origins reach back to the first years of the twentieth century when the Urban Military Academy was founded by Mary McDonnell. The boarding and day school was originally located in Hollywood (at Melrose and Wilcox) before moving to Brentwood.  In 1972, the new Brentwood School took over the old military academy.  A multi-campus independent K-12 Day School, it began as a college-preparatory high school and expanded to include elementary students and new campuses.  Its athletic fields are on the grounds of the West Los Angeles Veterans Administration.</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="itme" n="3">
                        <head>Brentwood Village, corner of Sunset and Barrington</head>
                        <p>This shopping area, a secondary retail area to that along San Vincente Boulevard, is a neighborhood gathering place.  Although it is close enough to UCLA that you might not want to stop here (unless you are interested in going into the northern parts of the Veteran’s Administration property), it is a good place for getting coffee, eating lunch, or getting a sense of what a small retail area is in a neighborhood like Brentwood.
                            
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    
                    
                    <div type="itme" n="4">
                        <head>The Archer School for Girls, 11725 Sunset Boulevard
                            
                        </head>
                        <p>If you have seen the film Chinatown, you have already seen this building which served as the site for the retirement home in which part of the mystery is solved.  The William Mosier-designed building opened in 1931 as the Eastern Star Home for Women, a residence for members of the Eastern Star and widows of the Masons.  The Archer School moved to the building in 1999, four years after its founding in the Pacific Palisades. <figure><graphic url=""></graphic><p>The Spanish Colonial Revival building provided housing and support services for Masonic women for almost 65 years.
                            Roy Hankey, photographer, 1980.
                            Los Angeles Public Library Photo Collection.
                        </p></figure> </p>
                    </div>
                    
                    
                    <div type="itme" n="5">
                        <head>Crestwood Hills / Crestwood Hills Park</head>
                        <p>Near the top of Kentner Canyon are Crestwood Hills Park and the community of Crestwood Hills.  Known initially as the Mutual Hills Tract, the housing and supporting institutions grew from the efforts of the families of four musicians (Ray Siegel, Leonard Krupnick, Jules Sukan, and Gene Komer) intrigued by the idea of cooperative housing.  Given the extreme housing shortage in Los Angeles in 1946, they felt that by buying land together they could build homes and amenities that they could not afford otherwise.  As they shared the idea with others, they eventually recruited 400 people interested in participating in their Mutual Housing Association.  Private and public were to coexist in the tract that was to include a park, nursery school, grocery store and gas station along with the homes of the members.  They interviewed architects, reviewed designed, and went to Washington, D.C. to argue with the Federal Housing Authority about its initial decision not to guarantee loans for homes built on the property.  Although various architects were involved in various stages of the development of the complex, A. Quincy Jones, Whitney R. Smith, and Edgardo Contini are credited as the design team.  <figure><graphic url=""></graphic><p>Advertisement for Crestwood Hills, c. 1947
                            http://crestwoodla.com/wp-content/uploads/2007/05/mha-gathering-01.jpg
                            http://crestwoodla.com/architecture/new-website/
                        </p></figure></p>
                    </div>
                    
                    
                    <div type="itme" n="6">
                        <head>Site of former O. J. Simpson estate, 360 N Rockingham Avenue</head>
                        <p>For almost a year beginning in June of 1994, media attention was riveted on O. J. Simpson and his home.  One of the many debated “facts” in Simpson’s trial for the murder of his former wife, Nicole, and Ron Brown was how fast Simpson could have driven from his home on Rockingham and her home on Bundy Drive.  Neighbors protested against the constant presence of the media that disturbed the usual quiet and seclusion of their street.  After he was acquitted and moved away, the house remained unsold.  It was eventually destroyed and replaced by a new home.</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    
                    <div type="itme" n="7">
                        <head>Mandeville Canyon (and Sunset Boulevard)</head>
                        <p>As you approach Mandeville Canyon, you reach the boundary of Brentwood and Pacific Palisades.  When the Los Angeles Athletic club purchased the land for the Riviera Country Club (in the Palisades), it included not only the land on which Paul Revere Middle School stands (according to the Los Angeles Times boundaries, half in the Palisades and half in Brentwood with a Brentwood address) but also a bit of the most southerly section of Mandeville Canyon north of Sunset (in Brentwood).  More important in shaping the settlement of Mandeville Canyon, however, was the Santa Monica Park Company’s sale of land from Mandeville Lane to Chalon Road to the Garden Foundation, Inc. in 1926.  To attract residents to its new subdivision, the Garden Foundation established a botanical garden at its center.  Naturalist H. C. Oakley supervised the design of the garden included plantings from all over the world that would be open to the public but would also be an important part of the marketing of the estates that were to be built on the hills around the garden.  The garden opened to an enthusiastic public in 1928, but the Depression intervened, effectively stopping sales of the estates that were to finance the upkeep of the garden.  </p>
                        <p>The less developed part of the canyon to the north attracted horse riders and hikers in the first decades of the 20th century.  It even served as one of the equestrian venues of the 1932 Olympics.  A particularly devastating flood in 1938 severely damaged the lower canyon.  It also effectively stopped the Garden Company’s further development of its land in the canyon.  Not until 1954 did the company start building homes again.  Not all development stopped, however.  Movie stars and other well-to-do Angelenos began, in the 1940s, to build “cabins” in the Canyon.  Their presence helped attract additional residents to the Canyon in the decades after World War II.   Several developers offered high-end homes further north in the steep canyon.  Residents still celebrate the area’s connection to nature – native plants and the remaining plants from the original garden, as well as wildlife that moves between the canyon and the Santa Monica Mountains National Recreation Area at is edges.</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="itme" n="2">
                        <head></head>
                        <p></p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="itme" n="2">
                        <head></head>
                        <p></p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="itme" n="2">
                        <head></head>
                        <p></p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="itme" n="2">
                        <head></head>
                        <p></p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="itme" n="2">
                        <head></head>
                        <p></p>
                    </div>
                    
                    
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
