<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Dowmtown</title>
                <author>Erin M. Coleman</author>
                <author>Janice L. Reiff</author>
                <respStmt>
                    <persName>Dawn Childress</persName>
                    <resp>TEI Encoder</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt><!-- just starting the convo on this part. -Dawn -->
                <publisher>UCLA Digital Library</publisher>
                <authority>A joint production of Jan Reiff, Dell Upton and the Sunset Boulevard Summer Knowledge Design Research Team:  Melanie Arias, Max D. Baumgarten, Erin Coleman, and Diane Ward.</authority>
                <date when="2015">Fall 2015</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc><!-- Information about the source -->
                <bibl>"Downtown," from <title>Seeing Sunset: Learning Los Angeles. A guide prepared for Students in GE66, LA: the Cluster</title>. University of California, Los Angeles.</bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <!-- we could also use type = entry or type=chapter-->
                
                <head>Downtown</head>
                <byline>Primary Authors: Erin M. Coleman &amp; Janice L. Reiff</byline>
                
                <!-- Could we move the title/author info to the header and pull from there, letting the XSL do the formatting? This might help us ensure consistent formatting here and the metadata will be in the header without duplication. -Dawn -->
        
                <p>For a profile of Downtown today, See the <title>Los Angeles Times</title>’ Mapping L.A. project at: http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/downtown/</p>
                
                <div type="bus_notes"><!-- If no Bus Notes, comment this section -->
                    <head>Bus Notes</head>
                    <p>...</p>
                </div>
                <!-- closes bus notes div -->
                
                <div type="sunset_notes">
                    <head>Sunset Notes</head>
                    <p>As Sunset Boulevard intersects Figueroa, its name changes to Cesar Chavez Avenue as you head east. After the death in 1993 of worker’s rights activist and co-founder of the National Farm Workers Association/United Farm Workers, the Los Angeles City council unanimously approved the name change of Brooklyn Avenue to Cesar Chavez Avenue.  When you look at older maps, you will notice a variety of street names that have disappeared.  In addition to noticing that Sunset once ended at Alameda Street, you will also find the name of Macy Street that continued the connection to Brooklyn Avenue through the part of Old Chinatown that was destroyed and relocated to build Union Station. </p>
                </div>
                <!-- closes sunset notes div -->
                
                <div type="historical_overview">
                    <head>Historical Overview</head>
                    <p>Los Angeles’ origins lie on the edges of what we now consider the city’s “downtown.” The first governor of California, Felipe de Neve, recruited settlers from the Mexican states of Sinaloa and Sonora to form and later found El Pueblo de la Reina de los Angeles in September of 1781. The first settlement developed along the Los Angeles River (<foreign>Rio Porcíuncula</foreign>), with some evidence that it may have been located a few blocks to the southeast of the modern-day El Pueblo Monument. The river itself shifted course several times, and the settlers had to relocate to higher grounds nearby. They understood the importance of access to water, especially with the sporadic rainfalls of Los Angeles, and immediately got to work constructing an irrigation system, with its major ditch known as the <foreign>Zanja Madre</foreign>. The settlers carved out agricultural plots to grow maize, wheat, beans, and later grapes and oranges. They, as the Spanish officials, relied on the paid labor of the Gabrieleño and Tongva population, who once dominated the Southland, to plow, sow, and harvest the crops along with expanding the irrigation system.
                        <figure>
                            <graphic url="http://uclalibrary.github.io/sunset/images/downtown_zanja.jpg"/>
                            <head>Washing clothes at the <foreign>Zanja Madre</foreign> [graphic]</head>
                            <p>"View of three women and two children washing clothes at the <foreign>Zanja Madre</foreign> (Mother Ditch). A few small buildings, visible throughout the image, appear to serve as barns. The <foreign>Zanja Madre</foreign> system ran from the Los Angeles River for more than a mile to the plaza, where the Olvera Street marketplace is now. Residents not only got their drinking water from the ditch, but the surrounding vineyards and farmland were also irrigated by its water."</p>
                            <ab type="attribution">Unknown, ca. 1900. Photo courtesy of the <ref type="url" target="http://photos.lapl.org/carlweb">Los Angeles Public Library Photo Collection</ref>.</ab>
                            <figDesc>Black and white photo of women and children washing clothes.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>Spanish colonial rule held until 1821, followed by a period of Mexican political power from 1821 until 1848 when the U.S. declared victory in its war with Mexico. The U.S. acquisition of California and the discovery of gold near Sacramento in the same year spurred the influx of Anglo and European settlers into what, in 1850, would become the State of California.  All of those developments helped to transform Los Angeles from an agricultural village into a bustling trading center of regional importance.  The extension of the transcontinental railway system to Los Angeles opened up easier access to the area for migrants from across the country.  Recruited by the railroads, the Los Angeles business community, and (after 1881) the <title>Los Angeles Times</title>, Anglos (as European Americans and European immigrants came to be called) flocked to the city, attracted by the climate, the availability of land, and the prospect of success that growing cities promised.  By the beginning of the 20th century, the city’s population which had been 1,610 in 1850 had grown to 102,479 by 1900 and much of that population lived in or nearby what is now considered downtown.</p>
                    
                    <p>One of the first things you will notice about Downtown Los Angeles is the 36-degree angle of its orientation as shown in Ord’s 1857 survey of the area below. While most American cities are designed with a clear grid of north-south and east-west routes, the heart of Los Angeles almost follows the 45 degree angled prescription that the Spanish Crown imposed on their colonies in the Americas and Philippines. According to Los Angeles historian D. J. Waldie, the deviation from the usual angle resulted from the path of the <foreign>Rio Porcíuncula</foreign> that was so critical to the city’s founding and early growth.  Many cartographers attempt to eliminate confusion by drawing maps of Downtown as if it had north –south and east-west streets, which serves to create more confusion oftentimes.
                        <figure>
                            <graphic url="http://uclalibrary.github.io/sunset/images/downtown_mapLA.jpg"/>
                            <head>Map of the city of Los Angeles showing the confirmed limits surveyed in August 1857 by Henry Hancock</head>
                            <p></p>
                            <ab type="attribution">Surveyed by E.O.C. Ord, Lt. U.S.A. and Wm. R. Hutton, assistant. August 29th 1849. Image courtesy of the <ref type="url" target="http://digital2.library.ucla.edu/viewItem.do?ark=21198/zz00096ffr">UCLA Library Digital Collections</ref>.</ab>
                            <figDesc>Map showing drainage, block and lot numbers, land ownership, buildings, fields, etc.</figDesc>
                        </figure>  
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>The Hancock map also reveals the ways in which the landscape and river shaped the land use and growth patterns of the city in its earliest years and that continued to shape it later.  Farmlands lay closer to the river where irrigation was easier.  The hilliest parts of the area serve as effective boundaries to growth.  As a result, the smaller, sub-divided plots of land are reaching toward the southwest in an area bounded by today’s streets of Figueroa, Pico, and Main -- much of what is considered downtown Los Angeles. 
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>Initially during the era when most Angelenos lived in the downtown area, it was also home to most of the functions they needed, as well as to most governmental offices, retail businesses, and even industries.  As more economically comfortable individuals moved away from the bustle that mix of activities brought with them, however, churches, schools and other such institutions followed them away from the central business district (CBD).  By 1920 when LA’s population reached 576,673 making it the 10th most populous city in the US, downtown Los Angeles had become a traffic nightmare as automobiles, street cars, buses, and pedestrians negotiated the canyons that the city’s so-called “height-limit” buildings created along it streets.  Some of downtown’s most prominent department stores also began to move to the rapidly growing communities developing elsewhere in the city.
                    <figure>
                        <graphic url="http://uclalibrary.github.io/sunset/images/downtown_broadway.jpg"/>
                        <head>Broadway north from Fourth Street, downtown Los Angeles, 1903-1905</head>
                        <p></p>
                        <ab type="attribution">Title Insurance and Trust, and C. C. Pierce Photography Collection, courtesy of the <ref type="url" target="http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/p15799coll65/id/1780">University of Southern California Libraries</ref> and the <ref type="url" target="http://www.californiahistoricalsociety.org">California Historical Society</ref>.</ab>
                        <figDesc>Photograph shows horse-drawn carriages, pedestrians, and a bicycle. A large boot with a sign "Cummings" sits on a building roof. Streetcar rails run down the street. The Broadway Department Store is visible.</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>That ongoing movement away from the downtown area left Los Angeles continued through the Depression, World War II, and the city’s boom years that followed.  As was the case with downtowns in other major urban areas, city officials and planners worried about what to do with the oldest part of the city that was still home to central government functions, offices of local, national and international businesses, an array of cultural institutions, and various retail establishments.  In the city that had helped to define urban sprawl, the downtown area, seemingly bounded by the freeways that led away from it as much as they had been planned to lead toward it, struggled with what the downtown should be.</p>
                    
                    <p>Discussions continued about what a civic center should be for the city that was fast becoming one of the nation’s largest but virtually all agreed that a vital and architecturally attractive governmental presence was important for downtown LA.  The architecturally stunning Los Angeles City Hall (200 N. Spring Street), completed in 1928, firmly located the civic center and established a <foreign>de facto</foreign> height limit for all of Los Angeles’ buildings for many decades when it reached above the existing height-limits established and then re-evaluated and reaffirmed by the City Council after the San Francisco earthquake of 1906.  The other important governmental building from the 1920s preceded it – the Hall of Justice (210 W. Temple Street) was opened in 1925.  The U.S. Post Office and Court House (north side of Temple between Spring and Main) was begun as a Work Projects Administration (WPA) construction project in 1937and completed in 1940, the third of three ever larger federal buildings in this area of Los Angeles.  Site of many important court cases, its arguably most notorious hearings were those conducted in 1947 by the House Un-American Activities Committee investigating communism in the movie industry.  Other buildings followed in the 1950s.  The Kenneth Hahn Hall of Administration (500 W. Temple) that houses many Los Angeles County officials and offices was built between 1952 and 1960.  Parker Center (150 N. Los Angeles Street), named for Los Angeles Police Chief William Parker and until recently the home of the Los Angeles Police Department, was completed in 1955 and the Los Angeles County Courthouse opened in 1958 at the Corner of Grand and 1st.  The most westerly of the Civic Center buildings was completed in 1964: the Department of Water and Power Building at 111 Hope Street.  The Criminal Courts Building (Temple between Broadway and Spring Street) was finished in 1973.  The State of California’s Ronald Reagan Building (300 S. Spring Street) opened in 1990, as did the federal government’s Roybal Center (255 E. Temple Street), named for Edward Roybal, Los Angeles City Council member and, subsequently, member of the U.S. House of Representatives.  The Metropolitan Detention Center (1989), operated by the Federal Bureau of Prisons, stands a bit apart from other federal buildings downtown.  It is located at 535 N. Alameda Street.  The State of California opened its District 7 Caltrans Headquarters in 2004 at 100 S. Main Street.  A new Los Angeles Police Headquarters Building opened across the street at 100 W. 1st Street late in 2009.  The city’s newest park – Grand Park, which opened in October 2012 – is part of this governmental complex, stretching from Grand Avenue to Spring Street between the governmental edifices on Temple and First.</p>
                    
                    <p>As Grand Avenue on Bunker Hill was cleared as part of the city’s slum clearance project (see Bunker Hill entry below), developers worked to create a cultural center in downtown as well.   Anchored on the south at 5th by the 1926 Central Library Building designed by Bertram Goodhue, Grand Avenue is home to the Music Center (located between Grand and Hope, Temple and 1st) which contains the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion (1964), Ahmanson Theatre (1967) and the Mark Taper Forum (1967).  The Music Center sits on land donated by the county, and was built using some $14 million in county revenue bonds and $20 million ($139 million in 2010 dollars) in private donations raised beginning in 1955 by Mrs. Chandler, wife of the publisher of the Los Angeles Times, and other individuals committed to making Los Angeles an important city in fine arts circles.  The fourth and newest building in the Music Center complex is Frank Gehry’s Walt Disney Concert Hall (111 S. Grand Avenue) opened in 2003.  These buildings are home to four resident companies: the Center Theatre Group, Los Angeles Master Chorale, the Los Angeles Opera, and the Los Angeles Philharmonic.
                        <figure>
                            <graphic url="http://uclalibrary.github.io/sunset/images/downtown_performances.jpg"/>
                            <head>Grand Performances, CRA/LA</head>
                            <p>The CRA also required that California Plaza provide a performing arts program.  The global arts program offers free performance during the summer that reflect  a wide range of global cultures that attract tens of thousands of visitors to the California Plaza.</p>
                            <ab type="attribution">Photo courtesy of <ref type="url" target="http://www.crala.org/internet-site/Other/Art_Program/artist_list/grand_performances.cfm">CRA/LA</ref>.</ab>
                            <figDesc>Color photo of crowd at an event in California Plaza.</figDesc>
                        </figure>
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>Also along Grand Avenue is MOCA Grand Avenue (250 S. Grand), opened in 1986 using funds raised by the Community Redevelopment Agency’s initiative that required 1.5% of the total budget of any development within CRA jurisdiction be earmarked for public art.  The construction of California Plaza (350 S. Grand Avenue), the private development surrounding MOCA (Museum of Contemporary Art) helped to finance the museum’s construction.  The Broad, currently under construction next to Disney Hall, will house the personal collection of Eli and Edythe Broad.  Across Grand the Broad and next door to MOCA is the Coburn School of Performing Arts and Conservatory of Music, which moved to Grand Avenue in 1998.</p>
                    
                    <p>An Adaptive Reuse Ordinance passed by the City Council in 1999 spurred the development of housing in downtown Los Angeles, begun in the 1980s with projects like the California Plaza which, when announced in 1983, proposed three office towers, 750 housing units, a hotel, a 12-theater cinema, parking for 4500 cars, and five acres of parks, gardens, terraces and waterfalls.  By 2008, there were more than 26,000 residential units in Downtown LA (15,000+ market rate units and 10,000+ affordable housing units).  Accentuating that change, Ralph’s opened the first supermarket located in downtown Los Angles for 50 years in the Market Lofts Building, a mixed use residential development located on W. 9th between S. Flower and S. Hope Streets.</p>
                    
                    <p>The location of that grocery store had much to do with a redevelopment effort begun in the late 1960s at Pico and Figueroa (1201 S. Figueroa) near where the Harbor Freeway meets the Santa Monica Freeway.  The Los Angeles Convention Center opened in 1971 to attract conventions to the city.  It has expanded several times since its opening to accommodate ever larger gatherings.  More important, it helped to serve as an anchor for an expanding entertainment complex nearby.  In 1999, the Anschutz Entertainment Group (AEG) opened the Staples Center, home of the Los Angeles Lakers, the Los Angeles Clippers, the Los Angeles Sparks, the Los Angeles Kings, the Pac-12 Basketball playoffs and countless other activities at 1111 S. Figueroa.  AEG expanded their operations with its L.A. Live complex, begun in 2005, next to Staples Center.  The complex contains apartments, movie and concert theaters, restaurants, and a 54-story hotel and condominium tower.  Nokia Theatre seats more than 7,000 and Club Nokia can accommodate crowds of more than 2,000 for live music and other cultural events.  The Grammy Museum opened there in 2008 and, in 2009, ESPN began broadcasting from its new studio in LA Live.  On September 28, 2012, the Los Angeles City Council unanimously approved still another AEG venture, subject to finding an NFL team that would move to Los Angeles – Farmers Field (named for the Farmers Insurance Group that signed a 30-year deal for naming rights).</p>
                    
                    <p>Future redevelopment efforts continue (see Broadway in the Points of Interest section).  However, the gentrification and redevelopment of downtown Los Angeles celebrated by many, has not been without a human cost as former single-room occupancy (SRO) buildings are torn down or converted into pricey apartments and condos.  Central City East, the area between Third and Seventh and Main and Alameda Streets in Downtown Los Angeles, is home to what has been estimated as the largest stable population of homeless people in the United States.  In 2006, the Ninth Circuit Court of Appeals ruled that the number of beds for the homeless was inadequate for the population and, as a result, suspended the city’s ban on camping within the boundaries provided above.  After initially appealing the ruling, the city settled the case with the ACLU and allowed sleeping on the city streets between 9:00 pm and 6:00 am until adequate units were built for the homeless population.  This part of downtown is also home to many charitable institutions that provide services to some of the city’s neediest residents and to organization like the Los Angeles Community Action Network (LA CAN) which work to organize and empower residents to work collectively and to help them in dealing with poverty and violence and to discover opportunities to escape them.</p> 
                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="bibliography">
                    <p>In addition to the individual sources and databases included above, the sources below were particularly useful:</p>
                   
                    <listBibl>
                        
                        <bibl><author>Central City Association.</author>  “Downtown’s Human Tragedy: It’s Not Acceptable Anymore- A Public Health and Safety Plan” (Central City Assocation 2002)  http://ccala.org/downloads/LegAffrsPublications/2002CCAhomelessnesswhitepaper.pdf</bibl>
                        
                        <bibl><author>City of Los Angeles, Planning Department.</author>  Broadway Theater and Entertainment District Design Guide: A Part of the General Plan, City of Los Angeles.  Los Angeles: City of Los Angeles Planning Department, 2009.   http://www.bringingbackbroadway.com/stellent/groups/electedofficials/@cd14_contributor/documents/contributor_web_content/lacityp_015468.pdf</bibl>
                        
                        <bibl><author>Fader, Steve.</author>  “Pershing Square Landmarks: A walking tour sponsored by the Los Angeles Conservancy.” 1986, revised 1993.  Online excerpt provided by Ruth Wallach, “Pershing Square Historic Background,” Public Art in LA, available at http://www.publicartinla.com/Downtown/figueroa/Pershing_Square_History/pershing_history.html.  Retrieved 3 October 2012.</bibl>
                        
                        <bibl><author> Hayden, Dolores.</author> The Power of Place: Urban Landscapes as Public History.  Cambridge, MA: MIT Press 1997.</bibl>
                        
                        <bibl>LA Curbed.  http://la.curbed.com/.</bibl>
                        <bibl>LA Fashion District.  http://fashiondistrict.org.</bibl>
                        
                        <bibl><author>Longstreth, Richard.</author>  The Drive-In, the Supermarket, and the Transformation of Los Angeles, 1914-1941.  Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2000.</bibl>
                        
                        <bibl>Los Angeles Downtown News.  http://www.ladowntownnews.com/</bibl>
                        
                        <bibl><author>Loukaitou-Sideris, Anastasia, and Gail Sansbury.</author> "Lost Streets of Bunker Hill." California History,  74: 4 (Winter 1995/1996), 394-407</bibl>
                        
                        <bibl><author>Welch, Paul.</author>  “The ‘Gay’ World Takes to the City Streets.” In “Homosexuality In America,”  Life (26 June 1964), 68-74</bibl>

                    </listBibl>
                    
                    <p>For further insights into the CRA’s urban renewal plans for Bunker Hill, you may find the following CRA publications online:</p>
                    
                    <listBibl>
                        <bibl>Amended Redevelopment Plan: http://www.crala.net/internet-site/Projects/Bunker_Hill/upload/bhredevelopmentplan.pdf</bibl>
                        <bibl>Area Map: http://www.crala.net/internet-site/Projects/Bunker_Hill/upload/Bunker-Hill-Map-in-PDF.pdf</bibl>
                        <bibl>Design for Development: http://www.crala.org/internet-site/Projects/Bunker_Hill/upload/BH_DFD.pdf</bibl>
                    </listBibl>
                   
                </div>
                
                <div type="Points_of_Interest">
                    <!-- tei-map -->
                    
                    <p>This section records the points of interest for three possible tours, one where you get off the bus at Third and Hill and walk through the Bunker Hill part of Downtown.  A second has you ride the bus to Hill and Olympic and walk to Downtown’s newest entertainment center:  LA Live.  The third has you walk (or ride) along Broadway before catching the bus for Chinatown and your return to campus.  If you are traveling with a day pass, you have the luxury of getting on and off the bus at will.  Hill Street and Broadway are a short block apart so it is easy to move between walking and riding.  Once you are past stop 5 below, anything on Hill or Broadway will be visible from the bus.  Other addresses will require you to get off the bus. </p>
                    
                    <div type="item" n="1">
                        <head><placeName>Orsini</placeName>, offices at 550 N. Figueroa</head>
                        <p>On the corner of Cesar Chavez and Figueroa you will see the Orsini apartment complex, built by developer Geoff Palmer. This complex, along with several of Palmer’s other housing complexes, illustrates some of the varied issues arising from gentrification.</p>
                        <p>During the construction of the first phase of Orsini in 2003, the construction crew razed the 1887 Giese house, the last remaining historic home in the neighborhood of Bunker Hill.   Because the demolition occurred without a permit, the city attempted to ban Palmer’s right to further develop the land for five years under its “scorched-earth ordinance.” Palmer retaliated by suing the City, and eventually the City and developer reached a compromise in which Palmer would be allowed to develop the land if he provided certain benefits to the community, such as parking spaces for the nearby Evans Community Adult School (717 N. Figueroa [Chinatown]), and a promise to provide affordable housing in the second and third phases of the project now located on either side of Cesar Chavez on either side of Figueroa.  This was neither the first nor last time Palmer would resort to suing the city of Los Angeles. In 2001 Palmer sued the city, challenging the mandates requiring him to provide affordable units in his Visconti apartment complex (1221 W. Third Street).  In 2009, he went on to sue the city again to avoid having to include affordable units in his Piero II (616 St. Paul) development.</p>
                        <p>Represented by the United Neighbors in Defense Against Displacement (UNIDAD), community members in South Los Angeles successfully gained leverage through the use of a Community Benefits Agreement (CBA). The CBA allowed UNIDAD to reach an agreement with Palmer in which he would provide low-income residents with affordable housing, health services, small business support, and job training in exchange for the community’s support in the approval of his Lorenzo project, a student housing community located near USC at 325 W. Adams Boulevard.</p>
                    </div>
                        
                    <div type="item" n="2">
                        <head><placeName>Ramón C. Cortines School of the Visual and Performing Arts</placeName>, 450 N. Grand Avenue </head>
                        <p>This distinctive-looking school, located near the site of Fort Moore and the second Los Angeles High School, opened in 2009.  In addition to a more traditional curriculum for students, there are also four Academies associated with the school: Dance, Music, Theater, and Visual Arts.  A decision to have the school make an architectural statement that would fit with Disney Hall three blocks away and its neighbor, the Cathedral of our Lady of the Angeles led Los Angeles Unified School District (LAUSD) to launch an international competition for the design. Federal funding, which would have been lost had the school not have been built, helped to make this a possibility It was won by Wolf Prix of the Austrian firm Coop Himmelb(l)au.  According to the Los Angeles Times’ California School Guide, the ethnic makeup of its student body of almost 1400 students is 67% Latino, 12.2% Black, 10.3% Asian, 9.3% White, and 1.3% Other.  66.5% of the students are eligible for free and reduced price lunch.</p>
                    </div>    
                        
                    <div type="item" n="3">
                        <head><placeName>Performing Arts Center of Los Angeles</placeName>, southeast corner of Grand and Temple</head>
                        <p>As you near the corner, you will see the Music/Performing Arts Center of Los Angeles County.  The building closest to you with its back on Temple is the Ahmanson Theater.  You may catch a glimpse of the Mark Taper Forum (1967) in the middle of the block.  The building at the far end of the block is the Dorothy Chandler Pavilion (1964).  When the bus turns, you may get a glimpse of Disney Hall, located across First Avenue from the Chandler.  All are worth visiting – to look at or to see a play or hear a performance of the Los Angeles Opera or the LA Phil.  The complex was designed by Welton Becket &amp; Associates, a prominent Los Angeles architectural firm from the 1930s through the 1980s.  Other buildings you will see in your travels include the Young Research Library, the Cinerama Dome and the Capitol Records Tower in Hollywood.</p>                             </div>
                        
                    <div type="item" n="4">
                        <head><placeName>Cathedral of Our Lady of the Angeles</placeName>, 555 W. Temple Street</head>
                        <p>Each Roman Catholic Diocese or Archdiocese, like the Los Angeles Archdiocese, must have a cathedral church that is the home church for the bishop or archbishop.  From 1876 until 1996, St. Vibiana’s Cathedral at Main and Second Streets served that function for Los Angeles.  When the 1994 Northridge earthquake severely damaged St. Vibiana’s, the archdiocese and preservationists engaged in a lengthy battle over whether the church should be torn down or restored.  In 1996, a compromise was forged in which the archdiocese would purchase a parking lot near the 101 freeway owned by Los Angeles County and the City of Los Angeles would get the St. Vibiana site.</p>
                        <p>The new cathedral took the name Our Lady of the Angeles and September 4, the day celebrated as the founding day of the city, was taken as her feast day.  The cathedral, which opened in 2002, was designed by Spanish-born architect José Rafael Moneo.  This is another site well-worth the visit, not only for its stunning architecture but also for the art work inside.
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="http://uclalibrary.github.io/sunset/images/downtown_vibiana.jpg"/>
                                <head>Exterior view of the St. Vibiana Cathedral soon after its completion on Main Street, Los Angeles, ca.1880</head>
                                <p>The smaller building with the white picket fence is the Union Rescue Mission.  As you consider the Cathedral of Our Lady of the Angels, consider the dramatic changes in church architecture between the 1871 building and the 2002 building.</p>
                                <ab type="attribute">Title Insurance and Trust Company. Photo courtesy of the <ref type="url" target="http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/cdm/ref/collection/p15799coll65/id/8852">University of Southern California Libraries</ref> and the <ref type="url" target="http://www.californiahistoricalsociety.org">California Historical Society</ref>.</ab>
                                <figDesc>The arabesque cathedral stands at center, a rose window positioned above the main entrance with a religious statue affixed at either side. It is surrounded by a wrought-iron fence. The cathedral's bell tower can be seen extending from the back of the building. To the left, two men stand and talk in front of the Union Rescue Mission's own picket fence. A typed caption underneath the image identifies the cathedral and the year.</figDesc>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <note>NOTE: The bus stop across from the Cathedral is an excellent place to disembark for your trip to the Plaza.  It is an easy walk down Temple to Los Angeles Street, where you will want to turn left (north), walk across the 101, past the Chinese-American Museum, and directly onto the Plaza.  You will catch the bus back to UCLA on Cesar Chavez on the other side of the Plaza.  If you are not going to the Plaza continue on the bus as it turns and goes southwest down Hill Street.</note>
                        
                    </div>
                        
                    <div type="item" n="5">
                        <head><placeName>Angelus Plaza</placeName>, 255 S. Hill Street</head>
                        <p>On the north side of Hill Street, between Second and Third Streets, notice the large housing complex known as Angelus Plaza. This affordable housing for the elderly was opened in 1980 and is a project strongly backed by Jan Perry, the Councilwoman for the 9th District (and current candidate for Los Angeles Mayor).  Reportedly the largest affordable housing community for older adults in the United States, it is home to some 1,300 adults with an average age of 82.</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="item" n="6">
                        <head><placeName>Third Street Tunnel</placeName> and <placeName>Ira Yellin Square</placeName>. Hill Street and Third Street</head>
                        <p>As the bus crosses Third Street, notice the tunnel to your right.  The tunnel was opened in 1901 as a way of connecting the part of the city that lay to the northwest of Bunker Hill with the rest of downtown.  If you walk back toward the tunnel when you get off the bus, you will see a sign commemorating Ira Yellin.  He, along with a small team of investors, bought and repaired the Bradbury building, Million Dollar Theater, and the Metropolitan Water District Headquarters, all of which you will see on Broadway. His restorations of Grand Central Market were completed with Community Redevelopment Agency and Metropolitan Transportation Authority funds.</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="box">
                        <head>Downtown Walking Tour 1:</head>
                        <p>(You should take at least one of these walks; if you have time you should consider doing several.  They are described so that you can get back on the bus if you want.  To walk the whole route is not difficult.)  FOR THIS TOUR, get off the bus at Third and Hill (the stop is across Third).</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="item" n="7">
                        <head><placeName>Bunker Hill</placeName></head>
                        <p>As you get off the get off the bus, look back toward where you came.  The imposing hill that you skirted on the bus (the seemingly empty blocks on the 1925 map above) is Bunker Hill.  While today, the hill is comprised primarily of high-end office space, it has gone through several phases in its history, from a primarily residential neighborhood, to a thriving mixed-use community, to its current form today.
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="http://uclalibrary.github.io/sunset/images/downtown_heartofLA.jpg"/>
                                <head>The Heart of Los Angeles</head>
                                <p></p>
                                <ab type="attribution">James H. Payne, Cartographer. c. 1925. Image courtesy of <ref type="url" target="http://digital2.library.ucla.edu/viewItem.do?ark=21198/zz001616pw">UCLA Library Digital Collections</ref>.
                                </ab>
                                <figDesc>Survey map of the Bunker Hill area of Los Angeles.</figDesc>
                            </figure>
                        </p>
                        <p>In 1867, Prudent Beaudry, a French Canadian who became Mayor of Los Angeles less than a decade later, purchased 20 acres of land at a sheriff’s auction, including parts of Bunker Hill. Stephen H. Mott, who became the secretary of the Los Angeles City Water Company, purchased the rest of the hill.  Beaudry recognized that in order to sell the plots of land on Bunker Hill to well-to-do Angelenos as he hoped, he would need to find a way to bring water to the top of the 375+ foot hill.  Along with two other investors, he formed the Los Angeles City Water Company, a private firm that used and sold Los Angeles River water.</p>
                        <p>In the 1880s, Bunker Hill gained prestige as an extremely fashionable place to live.  Ornate mansions populated its landscape as an elite class of doctors, lawyers and merchants made the hill their home.  As the Downtown grew more congested and newer neighborhoods further from the city center developed, elites abandoned Bunker Hill.  This move to outlying residential areas was part of a much larger trend across the nation.  Streetcars enabled this movement in the 19th century; automobiles facilitated it in the 1920s.  The post World War II national highway construction program also enabled and encouraged households to move away from central cities, leaving many downtown streets, by the 1950s, largely depopulated.</p>
                    </div>
                    
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
