<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Historic Edendale</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="article">
                <!-- we could also use type = entry or type=chapter-->
                
                <head>Historic Edendale</head>
                <byline>Primary Authors: Max D. Baumgarten</byline>
        
                
                <p>For a profile of Silver Lake today, 
                    see the Los Angeles Times’ Mapping L.A. project at 
                    http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/silver-lake/
                    For a profile of Echo Park today, 
                    see the <title>Los Angeles Times’</title> Mapping L.A. project at 
                    http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/echo-park/
                    
                </p>
                
                <div type="bus_notes">
                    <head>Bus Notes</head>
                    <p>The 2/302 bus makes frequent stops through Silver Lake and the neighborhood directly to the east, Echo Park. Silver Lake and Echo Park – particularly near the Sunset Junction district, the intersection of Sunset and Alvarado, and the intersection of Sunset and Echo Park Avenue -- are good places to get off the bus, people watch, grab a bite to eat, and use a restroom. Be aware that if you disembark in Silver Lake and later decide to continue taking the bus eastward, buses marked Alvardo will not go all the way downtown but will stop at Alvarado and Sunset in Echo Park. The bus driver will be helpful in answering questions about the bus route. 
                        
                    </p>
                </div>
                <!-- closes bus notes div -->
                
                <div type="sunset_notes">
                    <head>Sunset Notes</head>
                    <p>Sunset Boulevard went through many transformations as it stretched from Downtown to Hollywood.  Before Reservoir #4 was transformed into Echo Park Lake, the property on which the road now runs lay under the reservoir.  In 1886, the creation of Elysian Park led city officials to improve Elysian Park Avenue to make it possible for residents to get to the park.  Some of that  roadway eventually became part of what is now Sunset Boulevard. Late that summer, the City Council granted a franchise to the Ostrich Farm Railway to lay a one-line iron track on which a car would run to take Angelenos from downtown to the Ostrich Farm in Los Feliz.  That route, from the center line of Elysian Park Avenue “to Reservoir street; across Reservoir street, at a point at or near where Elysian Park avenue intersects Reservoir street; across Alvarado street junction ..; across Micheltorena street …, and across Effie Street,” (“The Ostrich Farm Railway,” Los AngelesTimes, August 31, 1886) also helped to determine the path of Sunset Boulevard.  By 1887, the OFR was bought up by the Los Angeles and Pacific Railway whose principles included Moses Wicks, J.W. Wolfskill and Senator Cornelius Cole – all of whom owned property further west and who were interested in extending the railway through the lower-lying areas that stretched toward Colegrove, Sunset, and Santa Monica outside the city limits.  Those who owned property along the proposed tracks inside the city limits (as most of what would eventually come to be known as Edendale/Echo Park/Silver Lake was) contributed to the improvement of the streets along the tracks and, in some instances, to the railway itself.  By the 1890s, former stretches of Elysian Park Avenue and Reservoir Street had been incorporated into Sunset Boulevard.  By the first decade of the 20th century, the stretch of Belleville that extended east to the Plaza had become part of Sunset Boulevard as well.</p>
                </div>
                <!-- closes sunset notes div -->
                
                <div type="historical_overview">
                    <head>Historical Overview</head>
                    <p> Echo Park and Silver Lake are located off Sunset Boulevard between East Hollywood and Chinatown. While Echo Park and Silver Lake were established independently of one another, and today are known as two distinct Los Angeles neighborhoods, their histories are best explained collectively: for much of the 20th Century, the area between Temple Street, Riverside Drive, Elysian Park, and Virgin Avenue, was known as Edendale. </p>
                    
                    <p>Development in Edendale dates back to 1868 when a water reservoir was built in what is now Echo Park Lake. In the late 1880s, a real estate investment group – led by former carriage maker Thomas Kelley – purchased and started to build up the 70 acres of land that surrounded the reservoir. Around the same time, the city of Los Angeles acquired a portion of land a few miles west that was eventually turned into the Ivanhoe reservoir (completed in 1906) and the Silver Lake reservoir (completed in 1907). Because these early developments were relatively removed from the rest of Los Angeles, light rails were constructed to help to connect Edendale with downtown Los Angeles and other parts of the city.  What we now know as Sunset Junction was once the place where Edendale’s main public transportation arteries came together.</p>
                    
                    <p>And yet, despite early development projects, Edendale was a relatively desolate area until 1909 when film magnate William Selig, who had established his Selig Polyscope Company in Chicago, moved west and established Los Angeles’ first permanent movie studio in Edendale. Other film studios followed: by 1912 the heart of the city’s dynamic film industry was located in Edendale.  Selig began the film industry’s move away from Edendale in 1913 when he established a zoo on Mission Road in Lincoln Heights with the many animals he had collected for his movies.  </p>
                    
                    <p>Most movie studios left the Edendale area by the early 1920s, but private developers and city planners continued to invest in the area’s infrastructure.  Silent film star Antonio Moreno developed the high-end, Mediterranean-inspired Moreno Highlands on the western side of the Silver Lake Reservoir. Edendale also attracted the attention of renowned architects Rudolf Schindler and Richard Neutra, who, as one historian explains, “dotted the hills with visionary designs that became icons of California modernism.” To provide Edendale hill dwellers with easy access to the streetcars below, the city built public stairways across the hillsides. While the hills of Edendale attracted the wealthy and artistic types, the area closer to Sunset Boulevard tended to draw a diverse array of working-class and middle-class Jews, blacks, Hispanics, and Russians, likely because it was one of the few places in Los Angeles without restrictive racial housing covenants. </p>
                    
                    <p>Edendale has also served as a breeding ground for nonconformist movements and ideas. Historian Daniel Hurewitz suggests that, “because of its rural-like isolation, it (Edendale) became a space at the margins of society that could be adopted as a site for contesting power, a place new identities, actions, and opportunities could be constructed.” From 1914 through 1915, Edendale was home to the radical Partido Liberal Mexicano commune.  And it was in Echo Park, right off Glendale Boulevard and Sunset Boulevard, that innovative celebrity evangelist Aimee Semple McPherson established Angelus Temple. By the 1930s and 1940s, Edendale became known as Los Angeles’ premiere bohemian enclave, home to a vibrant community of artists, writers, and progressive political organizations.</p>
                    
                    <p>With the removal of the Pacific Electric Railway and the subsequent construction of the Glendale Freeway down Allesandro Avenue, the name Edendale fell out of use. While Echo Park and Silver Lake thereafter became two distinct areas, no longer linked under the Edendale umbrella, they nevertheless continued to preserve the progressive, electric, and nontraditional ethos that defined Edendale. During the 1950s Echo Park was commonly referred to as “Red Gulch” because many blacklisted film professionals lived in the area. One of the nation’s first public gay rights protests during the 1960s was located at Black Cat Tavern in Silver Lake. And from the 1960s through the 1980s, Echo Park was home to the radical food cooperative, Food Conspiracy. </p>
                    
                    <p>Echo Park and Silver Lake have also been able to retain the ethnic diversity that characterized Edendale -- in fact, that is one of the defining features of the area today.  In the years following the Second World War, as many middle class white families left Echo Park and Silver Lake for the Westside and the Valley, the area became overwhelmingly Hispanic (primarily Mexican, Cuban, El Salvadorian, and Puerto Rican), and saw the entrance of a vibrant Asian (primarily Chinese, Japanese, Filipino, an Vietnamese) immigrant community into Echo Park.
                        
                    </p>
                    
                    <p>During the middle decades of 20th Century, Echo Park and Silver Lake became symbols of the urban blight that characterized much of mid-century Los Angeles. The construction of the Hollywood (101) Freeway destroyed much of the charming, small-scale housing around Echo Park Lake; tax bases, property values, and the housing stock drastically fell in the area off Sunset Boulevard; crime, violence, and the presence of juvenile gangs increased. The problems that burdened Echo Park in particular were virtually ignored by city leaders and absentee landlords. The area, in the words of the <title>Los Angeles Times</title>, became a “near slum.”</p>
                    
                    <p>And yet, the urban ills that afflicted Echo Park or Silver Lake were neither permanent nor irreversible. During the past three decades, these areas have been able to attract relatively affluent, usually white middle-class residents that are eager to live in a vibrant urban setting and are equipped with the social and political clout necessary to help improve Silver Lake and Echo Park. Signs of gentrification and urban renewal can be seen all along Sunset Boulevard, especially in Silver Lake. Indeed, in September of 2012, Forbes magazine named Silver Lake “America’s Best Hipster Neighborhood.”</p><p>
                        
                        Despite its benefits, gentrification and urban renewal have come at a steep price for many of the working-class – particularly Hispanic – residents of Echo Park and Silver Lake. In recent years, rising rents have increasingly pushed Hispanic families and business to the margins of the neighborhood.  Consequently, tensions between the middle-class whites and the working-class Hispanics over communal resources (public schools, transportation, neighborhood council representation) have become omnipresent. The most pressing question facing Silver Lake and Echo Park today is whether the social friction that manifests itself along racial and class lines can be solved in a way that helps to unite the area’s residents.  
                    </p>
                    
                    
                    
                </div>
                
                <div type="bibliography">
                    <p>In addition to the individual sources and databases included above, the sources below were particularly useful:  </p>
                    
                    <bibl><author>Echo Park Historical Society. </author> Historic Echo Park Neighborhood Guide.  n.d.  Available at http://dbase1.lapl.org/webpics/calindex/documents/13/522161.pdf.</bibl><bibl>
                       <author> Haynes, Lincoln. </author>“Other Views: Edendale--Where Stars Were Born.” <title>Los Angeles Times (1923 Current File)</title>. Los Angeles, Calif., United States, December 26, 1983.
                        http://search.proquest.com/docview/153664997/fulltextPDFHistoric Echo Park: The Website of the Echo Park Historical Society.  http://ephsnews.blogspot.com/</bibl><bibl>
                        <author>Hurewitz, Daniel. </author> <title>Bohemian Los Angeles and the Making of Modern Politics. </title> Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 2008.  </bibl><bibl>
                        <author>Matun, Alan </author>“Gay Community Gaining Tolerance, Prosperity in Northeast L.A.: Communication Barriers Down in Diverse Neighborhood Gays: Prospering, Being  Accepted in Northeast L.A.” Los Angeles Times. Los Angeles, Calif., United States, April 18, 1982. </bibl><bibl> http://search.proquest.com/hnplatimes/docview/153105993/138CEBBC4E24B5E4839/1?accountid=14512
                       <author> Pulido, Laura, Laura Barraclough &amp; Wendy Cheng.</author>  A People’s Guide to Los Angeles. Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press, 2012.</bibl><bibl>
                        “Silver Lake Reservoir: New Storage Basin in the Ivanhoe Canyon; Important Addition to City Water System; Ninety-three Acres Behind Big Steel Dam.” <title>Los Angeles Times.</title> Los Angeles, Calif.,  United States, November 26, 1906.   http://search.proquest.com/hnplatimes/docview/158967725/abstract?accountid=14512.</bibl><bibl>
                        <author>Stewart, Lynn. </author> "History: Silver Lake-Echo Park Plan Area.”  Unpublished typescript, 1979.  Los Angeles Public Library.  Available at http://dbase1.lapl.org/webpics/calindex/documents/02/219281.pdf</bibl><bibl>
                      <author>  Stolberg, Sheryl.</author> “L.A. Cubans Honor a Hero, Talk of Freedom in Havana: [Home Edition].” <title>Los  Angeles Times.</title> Los Angeles, Calif., United States, January 29, 1990.  http://search.proquest.com/docview/280964822/138BF427EB4209E351F/19?accountid=14512</bibl><bibl>
                        <author>Torgerson, Dial</author> “Which Way for Echo Park---Inner City Oasis or Slum?.” <title>Los Angeles Times.</title> Los  Angeles, Calif., United States, September 19, 1971.   http://search.proquest.com/hnplatimes/docview/156883898/139413D9BDB2D1F7A6A/1?acc untid=14512
                        
                    </bibl>
                   
                    <p>Note: While the Historical Overview section above presents a combined portrait of Silverlake and Echo Park, the points of interest below are split into each present day neighborhood as identified by the LA Times.</p>
                   
                </div>
                
                <div type="Points_of_Interest">
                    <head>Silverlake</head>
                    <div type="item" n="1">
                        
                        
                        <head>Sunset Junction, 4017 West Sunset Boulevard</head>
                        
                        <p>Sunset Junction is the informal name area for an area in southwest Silver Lake that runs down Sunset Boulevard between Fountain Avenue and Edgecliff Avenue. The name itself refers to a streetcar junction and commuter stop that was formed in 1905 at the Sunset and Santa Monica Boulevard intersection. At this intersection, two interurban railway lines – one travelling west on Sunset, the other down Santa Monica Boulevard – converged. The streetcar junction served Los Angeles’ public transportation needs until 1954, when the city’s streetcar lines were shutdown and replaced by public buses. 
                    </p>
                        
                        <p>Sunset Junction continued to be an integral part of city’s public landscape even after streetcars fell out of use. The city’s first public gay rights demonstrations, held in response to a violent police raid at the Black Cat Tavern, was located on the corner of Sunset and Santa Monica Boulevard.  During the 1970s and early 1980s, the area witnessed frequent conflicts between the relatively affluent, white gay community and the working-class Hispanic and Asian residents over issues related to gentrification. These neighborhood antagonisms led to the firebombing of a gay nightclub in 1980. The annual Sunset Junction Street Fair was first organized in 1980 as a community event that aimed to soothe neighborhood tensions.  As fair coordinator Thom Rafter, told the Los Angeles Times, “the idea is to generate a dialogue between the different elements of the community. Unless people start talking and mingling, they’ll never really grow and break down stereotypes about each other.” During the 1990s, the community-oriented Sunset Junction Street Fair morphed into a popular and heavily commercialized music festival.</p>
                        
                        <p>Sunset Junction is currently a popular destination among locals and visitors alike, home to a number of trendy boutiques, bars, cafes, and restaurants. 
                            
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="item" n="2">
                        
                        <head>Black Cat Tavern, 3909 W. Sunset Blvd.</head>
                        
                        <p>During the 1960s Silver Lake garnered a reputation as a gay-friendly area, though tensions existed between the gay community and local law enforcement. These hostilities reached a high point on New Years Eve, 1967 at the recently opened Black Cat Tavern. Undercover police raided the tavern, which was one of Los Angeles’ first openly gay bars, and proceeded to arrest and physically attack patrons. The violence spilled onto the street and a small riot ensued. The police charged fifteen people in total – thirteen with lewd conduct, two with drunkenness, and one with assault.  
                        </p>
                        
                        <p>Six weeks later in front of the Black Cat, about 200 community activists held the city’s first public demonstration in favor of gay rights, an event that helped to embolden the gay rights cause and establish links between the emerging gay liberation movement and other social movements of the 1960s. These events pre-dated the better-known, New York-based Stonewall Riots by two years. Black Cat Tavern was named a Los Angeles Historic-Cultural Monument on November 7, 2008; yet, the site itself (3909 Sunset Boulevard) is currently unoccupied, though can be distinguished by its purple exterior.</p>
                    </div>
                    
                    <div type="item" n="3">
                        
                        <head>Sunset Triangle Plaza, Sunset and Griffith Park Boulevard</head>
                        
                        <p>The recently constructed Sunset Triangle is Los Angeles City’s first pedestrian Plaza. Drawing inspiration from the innovative pedestrian plazas installed in New York City under the purview of Department of Transportation Commissioner, Janet Sadick-Khan, an organization called Living Streets LA spearheaded the pilot project. The Los Angeles City Planning Commission supported the project, recognizing its ability to rapidly provide more public space. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention funded the project. 
                        </p>
                    </div>  
                    <div type="item" n="4">
                        
                        <head>Micheltorena Stairway, 3324 Sunset Boulevard</head>
                        
                        <p>The stairways scattered across Echo Park and Silver Lake are relics of a Los Angeles before automobiles began to dominate the urban landscape. During the 1910s and 1920s, city planners and developers built public stairways in Edendale to provide residents that lived in the steep hills north of Sunset Boulevard with easy and direct access to the public transit stops and commercial establishments located off Sunset Boulevard. Because of frequent complaints from local residents during the 1980s regarding the safety and sanitation of the stairways, the Los Angles City Council withdrew some of the staircases from public use.  Yet, the Micheltorena Stairway is still open to the public. This long, straight stretch of 218 steps takes pedestrians from 3324 Sunset Boulevard up towards Effie Street and is currently a popular destination for urban hikers and exercise enthusiasts. While we encourage you to visit the stairway, please avoid walking the stairs at night.
                        </p>
                    </div>  
                    <div type="item" n="5">
                        
                        <head>Sunset &amp; Reno</head>
                        
                        <p>This cut illustrates the construction challenges along Sunset Boulevard due to its topography.  Much of this work was done with the assistance of federal funds during the Great Depression.  Unemployed workers were hired by the Works Progress Administration to widen and improve existing streets (like Sunset) and to construct new streets and roads as the city expanded into new areas.
                        </p>
                    </div>  
                    <div type="item" n="6">
                        
                        <head>Silverlake Reservoir Complex</head>
                        
                        <p>The Silver Lake Reservoir Complex is home to two distinct though adjacent concrete reservoirs -- Silver Lake and Ivanhoe. The story of the reservoirs began in the 1880s when the city of Los Angeles acquired empty land with the intention of creating an emergency water facility for the city’s ever-growing population. William Mulholland, the head of the Los Angeles Department of Water and Power, designed and spearheaded the construction of the reservoirs. He named the lower reservoir Silver Lake after the city’s Water Commissioner Harry Silver and the upper reservoir Ivanhoe after the original name of the area. Together, Ivanhoe (completed in 1906) and Silver Lake (completed in 1907) were able to hold 767 million gallons of water and supply the city with enough water for 20 days in case of an emergency.
                        </p>
                        <p>The reservoirs have undergone a variety of alterations since their construction over a century ago. In the 1920s, as the city’s demand for drinking water increased, the reservoirs were redesigned for everyday use.  In 1945 and 1975, the reservoirs were renovated to withstand earthquake damage. The reservoirs are still in use, providing water for the residents of South Los Angeles. In December of 2007, the Department of Water and Power announced that the reservoirs had become contaminated with an unusually high amount of the cancer-causing chemical bromate. The reservoirs were consequently drained and refilled.</p>
                        
                    </div>  
                    <div type="item" n="7">
                        
                        <head>Epitaph Records, 2798 Sunset Blvd.</head>
                        
                        <p>Not only is Los Angeles an important center for movies in the nation, but it is also a major site of music production. Though its façade is nondescript, Epitaph Records is housed in the large unmarked building at 2798 Sunset Boulevard. The label was created by Bad Religion guitarist, Brett Gurewitz. 
                            
                            
                        </p>
                    </div>  
                    <div type="item" n="8">
                        
                        <head>Happy Foot Sad Foot, Sunset Blvd. &amp; Benton Way</head>
                        
                        <p>The Foot Clinic sign at Sunset and Benton Way is known by locals as Happy Foot, Sad Foot. One side of the sign shows the distressed and bandaged foot displayed here, while the other shows a smiling, healthy and happy foot. Some have tattoos of the sign, while others believe the side of the sign they first see predicts whether their day will be a good or bad one. The sign now has wider notoriety as well from its appearance in David Foster Wallace’s writing along with that of Jonathan Lethem. 
                        </p>
                    </div>  
                    <div type="item" n="9">
                        
                        <head>Keystone Studios, 1712 Glendale Blvd.</head>
                        
                        <p>Movie producer Mack Sennett, with backing from the New York Motion Picture Company, established Keystone Studios in 1912. Keystone Studios was not the first movie studio to settle in Edendale -- that would be nearby Selig Polyscope Company -- but Keystone is often regarded as the most important studio of the silent era. Keystone Studios introduced slapstick style comedy to the silver screen and pioneered feature length films at a time when most studios were still dabbling in shorts films. Additionally, Keystone helped to launch of careers of Hollywood icons Charlie Chaplin, Fatty Arbuckle, Gloria Swanson, and Mabel Normand.  Keystone’s eminence was short lived though: following Sennett’s departure in 1917, Keystone entered a period of decline and ultimately closed its doors in 1935. While Keystone Studios was declared a historic landmark in 1982, the former location is currently a public storage facility.
                        </p>
                    </div>  
                   
                </div>
                <div type="Tour_Notes">
                    <p>
                        
                        Silver Lake’s Sunset Boulevard; Start at Sunset and Bates, End at Sunset and Silver Lake Boulevard. </p>
                        
               <p>         This walking tour of Silver Lake spans about 1.25 miles and will primarily – though not exclusively -- consist of a jaunt down Sunset Boulevard.  If you decide to take this tour, disembark at the corner of Sunset and Bates. Start walking eastward on Sunset. At 3909 Sunset, lies the former site of Black Cat Tavern; ask yourself what geographical, social, and political considerations helped to contribute to Silver Lake’s rise as a tolerant, gay-friendly counterculture destination? As you continue walking east on Sunset, you will enter the heart of the ever-trendy Sunset Junction district of Silver Lake. Intelligentsia Coffee and Casbah Café – both of which are located on the south side of the street – are good places to stop, use a restroom, and grab a quick bite to eat. </p><p>
                        
                        Walk a block and a half east on Sunset Boulevard; the Sunset Triangle plaza is located on north side of the street. Take a seat in the plaza, people watch, and observe your surroundings. Think about the ways in which the processes of gentrification have altered the demographics and infrastructure of Silver Lake? What is the relationship between gentrification and diversity? </p><p>
                        
                        From the Sunset Triangle Plaza, walk east three blocks to the intersection of Sunset and Micheltorena. The entrance to Micheltorena Stairway is located on the north side of the street; it’s highly recommend that you walk all the way up (and back down) this public stairway. Think about why the stairway was originally built and the how its uses have changed since the early 20th Century. You might want to avoid walking the stairway at night.  </p><p>
                        
                        Once you get back to Sunset, walk a few blocks east to the corner of Sunset and Silver Lake Boulevard, where you will get back on the 2/302 bus. 
                        
                        
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
