<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hollywood</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="article">
            <!-- we could also use type = entry or type=chapter-->

            <head>Hollywood</head>
            
             <figure>  
               <graphic url="http://emcaulay.bol.ucla.edu/sunset/images/hollywood_intro_image.jpg"></graphic>
              
             </figure>

            <note>For a profile of Hollywood
               today, see the L<title>os Angeles Times’</title> Mapping L.A. project at <ref type="url" target="http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/hollywood/">
                  http://projects.latimes.com/mapping-la/neighborhoods/neighborhood/hollywood/</ref></note>
            
            <byline>Primary Author: Melanie Schmidt Arias</byline>
            
            <div type="bus_notes">
               <head>Bus Notes</head>
               <p>The bus path through Hollywood is perhaps the most straightforward of all you will
                  encounter on your journeys. The 2/302 makes frequent stops in this neighborhood
                  and you will have no trouble getting back on if you get off at one of the
                  suggested stops in this neighborhood. The simplicity of the route and heavy
                  pedestrian/business traffic in the area make this a good place to stop and get
                  something to eat or drink. Most places where you do so will allow you to use their
                  restroom facilities, though you may need to ask for a key. If you disembark at
                     <placeName>Sunset and Vine</placeName>, you can find many options for food. If
                  you’d like to do some people watching, you can get something to go at the
                     <placeName>Trader Joe’s on Sunset and Hollywood
                  </placeName> (just walk north on Sunset), then carry your meal to the
                     <placeName>fountain in front of the Chase Bank</placeName> at <geogName>Sunset
                     and Vine</geogName>. More information on that bank, as well as the
                     <placeName>Hollywood Walk of Fame</placeName>, which you will walk on if you
                  stop, is below. </p>
            </div>
            <!-- closes bus notes div -->

            <div type="sunset_notes">
               <head>Sunset Notes</head>
               <p>By the <date from-iso="1880" to-iso="1899">end of the 19th century</date>,
                     <geogName>Sunset Boulevard</geogName> had been extended through
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> to the mouth of <placeName>Laurel
                     Canyon</placeName>. It was clear to ambitious Hollywood developers, however,
                  that it was not adequate for the town they hoped would grow up there. In <date
                     when-iso="1901">1901</date>, developers <persName>H. L. Whitley</persName> and
                     <persName>Griffith J. Griffith</persName> and representatives of the
                     <orgName>Los Angeles and Pacific Railway</orgName> invited the <orgName>Sunset
                     Boulevard Improvement Association</orgName> to Hollywood with developers to
                  advocate for the widening of <geogName>Sunset</geogName> and its extension from
                     <placeName>downtown Los Angeles</placeName> to the <geogName>sea</geogName>.
                  The Hollywood group was even more interested in the development of
                     <geogName>Hollywood Boulevard</geogName>, nearer and more important to them for
                  the development of the community they envisioned there. As you walk along both
                  streets, pay attention to the various indicators of how those two streets
                  developed in this most famous part of Los Angeles. </p>
               <figure>
                  
                  <graphic url="http://emcaulay.bol.ucla.edu/sunset/images/hollywood_map_ucla_1898.jpg"/>
                  <p>This 1898 map of Los Angeles
                     Country provides a glimpse into
                  Hollywood’s early history. The shaded areas are
                     Rancho La Brea and, in yellow, Rancho Los
                        Feliz. To help you locate yourself, at the right, the railroad
                     is on Western Avenue, Going north, it turns west on
                     Hollywood Boulevard before turning south on
                     Highland. From Sunset it
                     turn south again on today’s
                     Fairfax and back to the east on Foothill
                        Road (Santa Monica Boulevard).
                     Colegrove’s eastern and southern boundaries are
                     Gower and Melrose <ref target="http://digital2.library.ucla.edu/viewItem.do?ark=21198/zz00096df8">http://digital2.library.ucla.edu/viewItem.do?ark=21198/zz00096df8</ref>. </p>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <!-- closes sunset notes div -->

            <div type="historical_overview">
               <head>Historical Overview</head>
               <p>Once called the <placeName>Cahuenga</placeName> (from the <placeName>Tongva
                     Valley</placeName>, the neighborhood now known as
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> was briefly (<date from-iso="1903"
                     to-iso="1910">1903-1910</date>) an independently incorporated city.
                     <orgName>Spanish officials</orgName> granted its <placeName>very northwest
                     corner of Hollywood</placeName> to <persName>Jose Vincente Feliz</persName> in
                     <date when-iso="1795">1795</date>. A large portion of what is now
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> was given to <persName>Antonio Jose
                     Rocha</persName> and <persName>Nemisio Dominguez</persName> by the
                     <persName>Alcalde (mayor) of Los Angeles</persName> in <date when-iso="1828"
                     >1828</date>. Despite its proximity to one of the earliest roads into the
                     <placeName>San Fernando Valley</placeName>, the <geogName>Hollywood</geogName>
                  area remained a lightly settled agricultural area until the <date from-iso="1880"
                     to-iso="1889">1880s</date>. Then, several individuals began to lay plans for
                  urban development. One of the earliest was former U.S. Representative and Senator
                     <persName>Cornelius Cole</persName>. Cole, a lawyer, received 500 acres of land
                  in <placeName>Rancho La Brea</placeName> from <persName>Maj. Henry
                     Hancock</persName> in payment for successfully defending his ownership of that
                  rancho land following California being declared a state. In <date when-iso="1880"
                     >1880</date>, he moved to <placeName>Southern California</placeName> and
                  settled on the property that he platted  and named
                     <placeName>Colegrove</placeName>. Real estate developer <persName>H. H.
                     Wilcox</persName> began advertising his <placeName>Hollywood
                     development</placeName> in <date when-iso="1887">1887</date>. Stretching from
                     <geogName>Sunset</geogName> to north of <geogName>Prospect</geogName>
                     (<geogName>Hollywood Boulevard</geogName>) and roughly
                     <geogName>Whitley</geogName> to <geogName>Gower</geogName>,
                     <persName>Wilcox</persName> died before Hollywood boomed. 
                  
                  <figure>
                     
                     <graphic
                        url="http://emcaulay.bol.ucla.edu/sunset/map_of_hollywood_usc.jpg"
                     /><p>Advertisement for H. H. Wilcox &amp; Co.’s Hollywood Tract, 1887, http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/cdm/search/searchterm/chs-m17836/order/nosort?x=1348433105153</p>
                  </figure></p>

               <p>The first major successful development of what would become the city of
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> was orchestrated by <persName>H.J.
                     Whitley</persName>, who developed western towns for railroads before coming to
                     <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName> in the <date from-iso="1890" to-iso="1899"
                     >1890s</date>. That background was invaluable as he helped to establish
                     <geogName>Hollywood</geogName>. With other members of the <orgName>Los Angeles
                     and Pacific Boulevard and Development
                  Company</orgName>, he helped to build a
                     <placeName>Hollywood Hotel</placeName> on the corner of
                     <geogName>Hollywood</geogName> and <geogName>Highland</geogName> that
                     <persName>Wilcox</persName> could have only imagined. When it opened in <date
                     when-iso="1902">1902</date>, it helped to establish what would come be known as
                  "Hollywood" lifestyle, grand and surrounded with celebrity. The company's purchase
                  of real estate in the hills north of <geogName>Franklin</geogName> between
                     <geogName>Highland</geogName> and <geogName>Cahuenga Boulevard</geogName> for
                  the <placeName>Ocean View tract</placeName>, confirmed that lifestyle, especially
                     <date notBefore-iso="1918">after World War I</date> when movie stars began
                  moving into the area that came to be known as <placeName>Whitley
                     Heights</placeName>. He launched other projects that supported Hollywood’s
                  civic infrastructure: a bank, transportation links, and the improvement of its
                  main street, <geogName>Hollywood Boulevard</geogName>. In <date when-iso="1903"
                     >1903</date>, the city was incorporated by a vote of its residents and officers
                  elected, including <persName>G.T. Gower</persName>, for whom one of the area’s
                  prominent streets was named. Just <date when-iso="1910">seven years later</date>,
                  however, <placeName>the city</placeName> was annexed into <placeName>greater Los
                     Angeles</placeName> as growth made secure access to a water supply a major
                  concern.</p>

               <p>By the time <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> became part of <placeName>Los
                     Angeles</placeName>, the <orgName>movie industry</orgName> had begun moving
                  into the area to produce films, attracted by the varied landscapes for filming and
                  the open spaces necessary to create indoor sets and studios. Movie making had come
                  west from its original center in <placeName>New York City</placeName>, largely to
                  escape the monopoly control that the <orgName>Edison Studios</orgName> derived
                  from their control of the patents for film technology. The first LA movie studio,
                     <orgName>Selig-Polyscope</orgName>, located in nearby
                     <placeName>Edendale</placeName> in <date when-iso="1909">1909</date> and
                  several others joined it there. <date when-iso="1911">Two years later</date>,
                     <orgName>Nestor Studios</orgName> and 15 other independents moved some or all
                  of their operations to <placeName>Hollywood</placeName>. The area near
                     <geogName>Sunset</geogName> and <geogName>Gower</geogName> emerged as an
                  important center of production. 
                  
                  <figure>
                     <p>Map of the corner of Sunset and Gower, pieced together from 1919 Sanborn
                        Fire Insurance Maps available in the ProQuest Sanborn Map collection
                        available through YRL’s digital databases. Please see the <ref target="ss">Using Maps</ref>
                        (Learning Resources) to find the maps at Proquest</p>
                     <graphic url=""/>
                  </figure>
               </p>

               <!-- not sure if this was a paragraph break or just the way the document looked in Microsoft Word -->

               <p>Encouraged by the early real estate developers, <placeName>Hollywood</placeName>
                  quickly grew into the dominant site for movie production in the world, and the
                  film industry expanded its reach north over <placeName>Cahuenga Pass</placeName>
                  into the <placeName>San Fernando Valley</placeName> as well as other locations in
                  the <placeName>Los Angeles region</placeName>. <placeName>Hollywood</placeName>,
                  however, remained its center and the name of the community became synonymous with
                  the <orgName>American film industry</orgName>. The first film made in
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> was by <persName>D.W. Griffith</persName>, who
                  would later become infamous for the film <title>Birth of a Nation</title>. Profits
                  from that film helped support the creation of
                     <orgName>Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer</orgName> which competed with emerging players:
                     <orgName>Paramount Pictures</orgName>, which began as a distributor, and
                     <orgName>Warner Brothers</orgName>, a studio created by two Polish immigrant
                  brothers that unified a variety of film enterprises. Another important studio,
                     <orgName>United Artists</orgName>, was founded by <persName>D.W.
                     Griffith</persName>, <persName>Mary Pickford</persName>, <persName>Charlie
                     Chaplin</persName> and <persName>Douglas Fairbanks</persName>, who wanted a
                  studio controlled by filmmakers and stars rather than investors. </p>

               <p>With this cinematic action came an influx of people who worked in &#x2014; or
                  aspired to work in &#x2014; the industry. This influx of population created city
                  planning challenges for the neighborhood. Traffic back-ups, accidents, and road
                  construction, all constants of contemporary Los Angeles, were well known in the
                     <placeName>Cahuenga Pass</placeName> as city planners perennially struggled to
                  widen the roadways to meet the demand for automobile and, in the <date
                     from-iso="1900" to-iso="1949">first half of the 20th century</date>, public
                  transit between the <!-- is the "the" here correct? --><placeName>Los
                     Angeles</placeName> and the <placeName>San Fernando Valley</placeName>. The
                  neighborhoods of <placeName>Universal City</placeName> and <placeName>North
                     Hollywood</placeName> as well as the city of <placeName>Burbank</placeName> are
                  still home to movie and entertainment production industry work, from large studios
                  like <orgName>Disney</orgName> and <orgName>Universal</orgName> to smaller
                  post-production and editing shops as well as prop houses and paint stores catering
                  to the film industry. The <orgName>Pacific Electric Red Car</orgName>, however, no
                  longer runs an electric train down the center of the <placeName>Cahuenga
                     Pass</placeName> as it did <date from-iso="1911" to-iso="1952">from 1911 to
                     1952</date>. Public transit through the corridor is now limited to
                     <orgName>Metropolitan Transit Authority (MTA)</orgName> buses, which use the
                  same right of way as private cars on both <geogName>Cahuenga Boulevard</geogName>
                  and the <geogName>101 Freeway</geogName>. </p>

               <p>The nature of employment in the <orgName>movie industry</orgName> shaped both
                     <placeName>Hollywood's</placeName> residential patterns and architecture as
                  well. Seeking ways to emphasize <placeName>Hollywood's</placeName> glamour,
                     <persName>Whitely</persName><!-- typo? --> and his partners oversaw the
                  building of luxurious home sites in <placeName>Whitley Heights</placeName>, as the
                  former <placeName>Ocean View tract</placeName> was vigorously marketed <date
                     notBefore-iso="1918">following World War I</date>. Its success in attracting
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> and <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName> elites
                  led to the development of <placeName>Hollywoodland</placeName>, a subdivision that
                  emulated <placeName>Whitley Heights'</placeName> social aspirations, ostentatious
                  architecture, and its large <geogFeat>Whitley Heights sign</geogFeat> that was so
                  well-lighted that it was visible from <geogName>Wilshire Boulevard</geogName>.
                  Arguably <placeName>Hollywood's</placeName> most famous icon, <geogFeat>the
                     Hollywood sign</geogFeat>, is a well-maintained remnant of the
                     <geogFeat>HOLLYWOODLAND sign</geogFeat> used to advertise the real estate
                  offering of investors that included then Los Angeles Times publisher
                     <persName>Harry Chandler</persName>. Constructed for temporary use,
                     <geogFeat>the massive sign</geogFeat> became such a potent advertisement for
                  the movie industry and the neighborhood that it has been massively refurbished
                  several times by boosters. The “LAND” part of <geogFeat>the sign</geogFeat>
                  deteriorated relatively quickly and was never restored. The development itself
                  still exists east of <placeName>Lake Hollywood</placeName> and just south of
                     <placeName>Mt. Lee</placeName>, where the <geogFeat>Hollywood sign</geogFeat>
                  sits. 
                  <figure>
                     <p>The dedication of the original developer’s sign for Hollywoodland in 1923.
                        Image from The Bruce Torrence Hollywood Photograph Collection via AP,
                        http://photographyblog.dallasnews.com/files/2012/07/Hidden_Hollywood.1.jpg,
                        accessed September 7, 2012.</p>
                     <graphic
                        url="http://photographyblog.dallasnews.com/files/2012/07/Hidden_Hollywood.1.jpg"
                     />
                  </figure>
               </p>

               <p>Below <placeName>the sign</placeName> and the tony hillside developments stood the
                  housing for the lesser-paid workers of the motion picture industry, aspirants for
                  jobs in the movies, and those who worked in positions supporting it. Bungalow
                  courts, an architectural style that grouped several small cottages around a
                  central courtyard (or later driveway), appeared throughout <placeName>Southern
                     California</placeName> and especially in <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> where
                  they provided relatively affordable housing for the growing influx of out-of-town
                  and out-of-state migrants seeking employment in the film industry, both on-screen
                  and behind the scenes. As the courts grew fashionable, larger and more luxurious
                  versions were built to cater to wealthier <placeName>Hollywood</placeName>
                  residents. Still another kind of housing appeared that sheltered young single
                  women coming to <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> looking for jobs. Boarding houses
                  provided some with housing. The most famous, however, was the <placeName>Hollywood
                     Studio Club</placeName> run by the <orgName>YWCA</orgName> that, from <date
                     from-iso="1916" to-iso="1975">1916 to 1975</date>, housed more than 10,000
                  women in a chaperoned dormitory-type setting. 
                  <figure>
                     <p>View of the Spanish style Grauman Court Bungalow apartments located on
                        Melrose between Alexandria and Kenmore Avenues in Hollywood. The complex
                        included seven stores, a completely furnished doctor’s apartment, and
                        gardens filled with California plants. Los Angeles Public Library
                        http://photos.lapl.org/carlweb/jsp/FullRecord?databaseID=968&amp;record=3&amp;controlNumber=73940 </p>
                     <graphic url="http://jpg3.lapl.org/pics42/00070644.jpg"/>
                  </figure>
               </p>

               <p>Several other forms of iconic California architecture can also be found in
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName>. Arts and Crafts-style Craftsman bungalows dot
                  the smaller residential blocks perpendicular to <geogName>Sunset</geogName>. Many
                  of these homes were also altered by the rise of the film industry, divided into
                  smaller units or transformed into boarding houses. Other iconic
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> buildings, including <placeName>Grauman’s
                     Egyptian</placeName> and <placeName>Chinese Theaters</placeName>, were built in
                  the <date from-iso="1920" to-iso="1929">1920s</date> as Hollywood grew as a
                  national and international symbol of lavish, opulent good life. <persName>Sid
                     Grauman</persName> himself, however, first struck it rich in the area’s
                  oilfields. The <placeName>Church of the Blessed Sacrament</placeName> on
                     <geogName>Sunset</geogName> was first built in the <date from-iso="1920"
                     to-iso="1929">1920s</date> in Italian Renaissance style, then renovated into
                  its present Spanish Colonial Renaissance style in the early <date from-iso="1950"
                     to-iso="1959">1950s</date>.</p>

               <p> During the <date from-iso="1940" to-iso="1959">1940s and 1950s</date>, Hollywood
                  continued to grow as an industry and a symbol, although many productions were
                  being relocated to outlying areas that now dominate movie production. At the same
                  time, the music industry was increasingly interested in building its own
                  connection to Hollywood and the Hollywood image. One great icon of that growing
                  relationship is the <placeName>Capitol Records Tower</placeName>, completed in
                     <date when-iso="1956">1956</date>. More famous sites at the nexus of film and
                  music are still evident along the <geogName>Sunset Strip</geogName> in
                     <placeName>West Hollywood</placeName>. In this era, the global Cold War caught
                  up with the film industry, and numerous investigations were launched into alleged
                  communist infiltrations. </p>

               <p> While "Hollywood" continued to dominate the movie industry through the <date
                     from-iso="1960" to-iso="1969">1960s</date>, changes in the industry meant
                  changes for the neighborhood. The neighborhood itself was no longer able to count
                  of<!-- typo? --> the film industry as its economic engine, owing in part to the
                  rise of television and in part to the continued dispersal of production,
                  increasingly overseas as well as to other parts of town. Neighborhood boosters
                  began planning to "restore" Hollywood by capitalizing on entertainment industry
                  tourism and the Hollywood image to benefit the actual community. The
                     <geogName>Hollywood Walk of Fame</geogName>, for example, was conceived and
                  constructed at this time. Efforts to urbanize the area also led to the
                  construction of some of <placeName>Los Angeles'</placeName> taller skyscrapers
                  there. The <placeName>Home Savings and Loan (now Chase bank)</placeName> on the
                  Northeast corner of <geogName>Sunset</geogName> and <geogName>Vine</geogName>
                     (<placeName>8150 Sunset Boulevard</placeName>) dates to that period. It was one
                  of many buildings <persName>Millard Sheets</persName> designed for
                     <persName>Howard Ahmanson</persName>, who transformed <orgName>Home
                     Savings</orgName> into the country's largest savings and loans as he helped to
                  finance <placeName>Los Angeles'</placeName>
                  <date>post-World War II</date> construction boom. The buildings he commissioned
                  reflect <persName>Ahmanson's</persName>
                 interest in enhancing the architecture and
                  art of <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName>, and this particular <placeName>Home
                     Savings bank</placeName> features a period mosaic of Hollywood stars as well as
                  Europa's Flight, a sculpture by <persName>Paul Manship</persName>. Also notable
                  for its architecture, as well as its role in <placeName>Los Angeles'</placeName>
                  labor history, is the <placeName>Screen Actors’ Guild National Headquarters
                     building</placeName> (<placeName>7750 Sunset Boulevard</placeName>), which
                  served as <orgName>SAG</orgName> headquarters from the <date from-iso="1954"
                     to-iso="1989">mid-1950s through the late 1980s</date>. </p>

               <p xml:id="h_p999"> The <date from-iso="1970" to-iso="1989">1970s and 1980s</date>
                  marked a period of significant neighborhood change for
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName>. National and local factors contributed to
                  this decline. <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> like many densely populated urban
                  areas, was impacted by a stagnant economy. Locally, the growth of punk and then
                  glam rock music, much of which was performed and recorded in
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> and <placeName>West Hollywood</placeName> by
                  bands living not far off in the <placeName>Hollywood Hills</placeName>, drew large
                  numbers of young people to the area, many of whom stayed and lived on the street.
                  Homeless youth became a major focus of social services in the area in the <date
                     from-iso="1980" to-iso="1989">1980s</date>. The <date from-iso="1970"
                     to-iso="1989">1970s and 1980s</date> also saw numerous protests around social
                  issues including ones against redevelopment that destroyed affordable housing in
                  the community as well as against rising crime in the area. During <date
                     from-iso="1970" to-iso="1989">those decades</date>, the neighborhood also saw a
                  change in demographics as immigrants from many countries moved into the area. 
                  <figure>
                     <p>An anti-prostitution protest on Sunset Boulevard, 1981. From the LAPL’s
                        Herald Examiner Collection.
                        http://photos.lapl.org/carlweb/jsp/DoSearch?databaseID=968&amp;terms=5025641&amp;index=z </p>
                     <graphic url="http://jpg1.lapl.org/00092/00092553.jpg"/>
                  </figure>
               </p>

               <p>New immigration streams to the U.S. increased the presence of <orgName>Central
                     Americans</orgName>, <orgName>Armenians</orgName>, <orgName>Filipinos</orgName>
                  and <orgName>Thais</orgName> in various waves. For some, like the
                     <orgName>Filipinos</orgName>, who had come to work in
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> decades earlier, and the
                     <orgName>Armenians</orgName>, who often had ties to
                     <placeName>Glendale’s</placeName> large Armenian community, moving to
                     <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> built on long established local connections.
                  For others, <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> represented a refuge from more
                  dangerous neighborhoods in <placeName>Los Angeles</placeName> as well as in other
                  nations. For many, <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> was a temporary stop on the
                  way to still another neighborhood elsewhere in the city or its suburbs. </p>

               <!-- lisa stopped doing in-depth tagging here; will come back to this later May 7 2014 -->

               <p>In 1986, the Los Angeles City Council adopted a redevelopment plan intended to
                  revitalize the increasingly blighted area. In amended form, the Hollywood
                  Redevelopment Plan continues to guide urban redevelopment efforts in the area.
                  Efforts have been funded in part by Community Development Block Grants from the
                  federal government, a form of grant which allows for many different types of
                  projects to be undertaken by participating cities with the intent of directly or,
                  more often, indirectly, fostering the creation of safe and affordable housing for
                  low- and moderate- income households. The redevelopment of the commercial and
                  residential space at <placeName>Hollywood and Highland</placeName>, where the Academy Awards or “Oscars”
                  have recently been presented is perhaps the most notable of the projects completed
                  in this effort. Examples are also visible along Sunset, restoration of the
                  <placeName>ArcLight Cinerama dome (6360 Sunset Boulevard)</placeName> and creation of associated parking
                  structures, as well as the commercial spaces at <placeName>Sunset and Vine</placeName>. The success and
                  wisdom of this tourism and density-based approach to rebuilding the area is
                  disputed by some planners and activists. Although the actual work of making film
                  and television continues to decline in Hollywood and in Los Angeles in general,
                  Hollywood has seen tourism and businesses return in recent years. </p>


            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
               <p>In addition to the individual sources and databases included above, the sources
                  below were particularly useful: </p>

               <bibl><author>Ford, Darryl.</author> "Columbia Square: 15 Year Development Agreement
                  Approved by City Council." <title>Hollywood Unbound</title>
                  <date>(30 March 2011)</date>. <ref>http://www.hollywoodunbound.com/2011/03/columbia-square-15-year-development.html.</ref>
                  Accessed 25 September 2012.</bibl>

               <bibl>
                  <author>Fredrich, Otto.</author>
                  <title>City of Nets: A Portrait of Hollywood in the 1940s.</title> New York:
                  HarperCollins, <date>1986</date>.</bibl>

               <bibl>
                  <author>Keith, Gaelyn Whitley.</author>
                  <title>The Father of Hollywood.</title> Mustang. OK: Tate Publishing,
                     <date>2010</date>.</bibl>

               <bibl>
                  <author>Kenaga. Heidi.</author> "Making the 'Studio Girl': The Hollywood Studio
                  Club and the industry regulation of female labour." <title>Film History</title>,
                  18:2 (2006), 129-139.</bibl>

               <bibl>
                  <author>The Hollywood Sign Trust.</author> "Our History." Hollywoodsign.org. <ref>http://www.hollywoodsign.org/historyofthesign</ref> (accessed September 7,
                  2012).</bibl>

               <bibl><author> Kotkin, Joel.</author> "Let L.A. Be L.A." <title>City Journal</title>
                  22, no. 3 (Summer 2012). <ref>
                     http://www.city-journal.org/2012/22_3_snd-los-angeles.html</ref> (accessed
                  September 7, 2012).</bibl>

               <bibl>
                  <author>Mallory, Mary and Hollywood Heritage, Inc.</author>
                  <title>Hollywoodland.</title> Charleston, SC: Arcadia Publishing,
                     <date>2011.</date></bibl>

               <bibl>
                  <author>Shiel, Mark.</author>
                  <title>Hollywood Cinema and the Real Los Angeles.</title> London, UK: Reaktion
                  Books, <date>2012.</date></bibl>
               <bibl>
                  <author>Tracy, Kathy.</author> "Church of the Blessed Sacrament Parish History,
                  2004 Edition." BlessedSacramentHollywood.com. <ref>http://blessedsacramenthollywood.org/history/</ref> (accessed September 7,
                  2012).</bibl>

               <bibl>
                  <author>Wanamaker, Marc and Robert W. Nudelman. </author><title>Early
                     Hollywood.</title> Charleston, SC: Arcadia Publishing,
                  <date>2007.</date></bibl>

               <bibl> Whitley Heights. <ref>http://whitleyheights.org/about.html.</ref> Accessed 17 September
                     <date>2012.</date>
               </bibl>
            </div>
      
            <div type="Points_of_Interest">
               <div type="item" n="1">
                  <head><placeName>Screen Actors Guild National Headquarters (former 1956-86), 7750 Sunset Boulevard (southeast corner of Sunset &amp; Genesee)</placeName></head>
                  <p>
                     Founded in 1933, the Screen Actors Guild was founded by actors unhappy with the studio contract system that tied them to a particular studio for a multi-year contract during which they had very limited control over their working conditions and the roles that they played. The founders of SAG were members of the live theater workers guild that advocated for actors on Broadway, the Actors Equity Association, and it served as a model. SAG’s first organizing success came in improving working conditions and hours for workers, and through the 1930s the Guild for greater labor rights for actors. The first major change was a California Supreme Court decision interpreting the duration of actors’ contracts with the studios in terms of calendar time rather than time worked. Subsequent changes included negotiations for payment to actors of a percentage of a film’s box office receipts and then, as TV entered the entertainment milieu, the right to collect fees for commercials, TV work and finally for films aired on TV. That concession was won following a 1960 strike with illustrated the power of collective labor organizing in the industry. SAG was also instrumental in securing pension and health care benefits. Ronald Reagan served as president of SAG from 1947-1952, years in which many actors and other involved in the movie industry were under investigation by the House Un-American Activities Committee.   In 2012, SAG merge with the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists to create SAT-AFTRA.  Currently headquartered at Museum Square (5757 Wilshire Boulevard), the union was also located in the Hollywood Congregational Church (7065 Hollywood Boulevard), the Hollywood Professional Building (7046 Hollywood Boulevard), the Constance Bennett Building (8743 Sunset Boulevard), and the Hollywood Center Building (1655 N. Cherokee Avenue).                   </p>
                  
                  <p>Located across the street is a union hall for the International Alliance of Theatrical Stage Employees (IATSE), originally chartered by the American Federation of Labor in 1893 as the National Alliance of Theatrical State Employees.  The union represents many craft workers in the film, theater, and related industries.</p>
                  
               </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="2">
                  
                  <head><placeName>Hollywood High School, 1521 N. Highland Avenue (corner of Sunset and Highland)</placeName></head>
                  
                  <p> Hollywood High was founded to serve the municipality of Hollywood in 1903, and has been at its present location since 1904. The school has historic significance in both culture and architecture. Culturally, the school produced a notable number of alumni who went on to fame in various aspects of the entertainment industry, from Lon Cheney to Sarah Jessica Parker. The school was added to the National Register of Historic Places in 2012, in recognition of its architectural history. The campus includes a number of buildings designed or redesigned by regional architectural firm Marsh, Smith and Powell in the PWA Moderne style reflected the utilitarianism of the New Deal Public Works Administration program for which it was named. The PWA’s  work on the school was precipitated by the destruction of the initial building by the Long Beach earthquake of 1933. The interior of the library features a New Deal mural illustrating the development of Hollywood. Many other campus buildings share this style and were designed by the same firm. One exception is the Auditorium, which was redone in the 1950s by the firm Marston and Weston in a Mid-Century Modern style. In 2002, Los Angeles-based artist Eloy Torrez painted the mural “Portrait of Hollywood” on the outside of the Auditorium that highlighted the ethnic diversity of Hollywood celebrities, some of whom were graduates of Hollywood High.</p>
                  
                  <p>The history of Hollywood High also reflects the history of the broader neighborhood, which struggled and declined in the 1970s and 1980s as the flight of many studios to other neighborhoods exacerbated Hollywood’s experience of the national trend of decline in center city areas. During this period, the school saw increasing enrollment from Los Angeles’ immigrant communities, particularly those fleeing instability in their home countries such as Central Americans and Armenians. Today, the student body is predominantly Latino and includes immigrants from many of these same countries. 40% are classified as English-language learners and 3 out of four students have family incomes that qualify them for free or reduced cost meals.
                  </p>
                  
               </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="3">
               
                  <head><placeName>House, 6722 Sunset Boulevard (south side of Sunset between Mc Cadden and Las Palmas)</placeName></head>
              
                  <p>Nestled in what appears to be the parking lot of the Hollywood Center Motel is one of Hollywood’s earliest homes.  According to the Los Angeles County Assessor, the home was built in 1901 and effectively built in 1922.</p>
               
               </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="4">
                  
                  <head><placeName>Crossroads of the World, 6671 Sunset Boulevard (Sunset just east ofLas Palmas)</placeName></head>
                  
                  <p>Crossroads of the World provides an excellent reminder of the way facades sometimes hide what is inside or behind a building or street front.  Immediately noticeable from its imposing art deco tower atop which an eight-foot globe sits and its streamline modern front, it is easy to miss the much larger development that is a very early shopping mall.  Designed in 1936 by architect Robert V. Derrah for Ella Crawford, the building that immediately catches your eye looks like an ocean liner and was surrounded by two-story cottages in a variety of international architectural styles, among them French, Turkish, Italian, Persian, Mexican, Algerian, Swedish, New England, and California.  Crawford, the widow of the Hollywood politician and murdered real estate man Charles Crawford, built the retail and studio space on the site of his former Sunset Boulevard office.  According to the Los Angeles Times that reported on the star-studded grand opening in October 1936, her plans called for more than a hundred shops, studios and eateries.  Like other locations on Sunset, the Crossroads fell into disrepair in the 1960s and 70s.  Now a Los Angeles Historic-Cultural landmark, it was purchased and restore by Morton La Kretz.  Today it is home to a number of offices, including those of the Hollywood Arts Council and the religious fellowship of Eckankar. 
                     
                     <figure>
                     <graphic url="http://jpg1.lapl.org/pics45/00042476.jpg"></graphic>
                     <p>Crossroads of the World [nd] Los Angeles Public Library http://jpg1.lapl.org/pics45/00042476.jpg
                        http://photos.lapl.org/carlweb/jsp/FullRecord?databaseID=968&amp;record=26&amp;controlNumber=47148
                     </p>
                  </figure>
                  </p>
                  
               </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="5">
                  
                  <head><placeName>Church of the Blessed Sacrament, 6657 Sunset Boulevard (near the corner of Sunset &amp; Cherokee)</placeName></head>
                  
                  <p>The Church of the Blessed Sacrament was first established on Hollywood Boulevard in 1904, along with a Parish School. In 1914, the church was placed in the control of the Jesuits, whose presence in greater Los Angeles already included Loyola Marymount University. Through the 1920s as the early film studios boomed in the area, Blessed Sacrament also grew as both a church and a center for community organizations, including the first group for the actors and authors who worked in Hollywood which became the Writer’s Guild and the Screen Actors’ Guild. As the church grew, the studio themselves also participated in fundraising which helped the church move to an expanded location on Sunset Boulevard near the Sunset Strip. The Church of the Blessed Sacrament on Sunset was first built in the 1920s in Italian Renaissance style, then renovated into its present Spanish Colonial Renaissance style in the early 1950s. As the neighborhood changed in ethnic composition through the second half of the 20th century, Blessed Sacrament began to serve the area’s growing Latino population. The church provided living space in a Hollywood apartment building for refugees from Central America, and still provides social services for low-income and homeless residents of Hollywood. 
                     
                  </p>
                  
                 
                  
               </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="6">
                  <head><placeName>Cahuenga Pass (the pass is north of you as you ride between Highland and Cahuenga Blvd)</placeName></head>
                  
                  <p>The Cahuenga Pass links Hollywood (once the Cahuenga Valley) to the San Fernando Valley. While the area was once a rural, farm-like environment where travelers sometimes faced the threat of bandits, it evolved into an increasingly important transportation corridor as Hollywood, Downtown LA and the San Fernando Valley grew in population and as residents of one area increasingly travelled to another for work. While in the 1890s, it was popular to transit the pass by bicycle, car traffic emerged as a concern on the road through the pass as early as the 1920s, and concerns about automobile accidents and runaway cars on the downhill grade into Hollywood began even earlier. Pacific Electric’s Red Cars ran on the San Fernando Valley line through the pass as early as 1913, but auto traffic continued to vex the corridor. A highway was constructed beginning in the 1920s, and was subsequently widened, nevertheless, increasing population led to rising demand which the roads never met. Plans for an even wider “freeway” called the Hollywood Freeway were drawn up as early as the 1940s, and work was finally completed on what is still the Hollywood Freeway in 1954. The creation of the freeway prompted the closure of the Red Car service in 1952, and the right of way along which the trolley travelled through the pass was paved over in order to widen the freeway a few years later. The transit development of the Cahuenga Pass reflects other related stories including the development of Highway 2 to the east and the 405 through the Sepulveda Pass to the west. <figure>
                     <graphic url="sss"></graphic>
                     <p>Looking North from point South of Whitley Terrace, Hollywood Freeway, 1952
                        USC Digital Library, Los Angeles Examiner Negatives
                        http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/assetserver/controller/view/EXM-N-9604-010~3
                        http://digitallibrary.usc.edu/search/controller/view/examiner-m18849.html?x=1348627791199
                     </p>
                  </figure> </p>
               </div>
              
              <div type="item" n="7">
                 <head><placeName>Hollywood Post Office 1615 Wilcox Avenue</placeName>  (just over one block north of Sunset on Wilcox)</head>

                 <p>The Hollywood Branch of the United States Post Office is an excellent example of the buildings constructed under the auspices of the Works Progress Administration (WPA), an important New Deal agency that provided jobs for unemployed workers during the Great Depression.  The well-known Art Deco architect Claud Beelman designed the building that has inside it a bas-relief entitled “The Horseman.”  Created by artist Gordon Newell, that piece was also commissioned by the WPA’s Federal Art Project.</p>
            </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="8">
                  <head><placeName>Home Savings Bank (now Chase Bank) 1500 Vine Street</placeName> (corner of Sunset and Vine)</head>
                  
                  <p>Located on the Northeast Corner of Sunset and Vine, the Home Savings Bank was opened in 1968. The building was commissioned by Howard Ahmanson Sr. as one of the last in a nearly two decade long series of branches of the Home Savings banks Ahmanson had designed by Millard Sheets. The bronze sculpture and fountain that stand before the building were also a part of the project. Ahmanson purportedly asked Sheets to design building which would liven up the boring architecture of Los Angeles’ business districts. Sheets designed more than 40 buildings for Ahmanson, and many have characteristics reflecting midcentury modern design as well as large entry sculptures and tile mosaics. The tile mosaic at the Sunset and Vine location highlights the movie industry. The fountain in the entrance court features a sculpture by Paul Manship called the Flight of Europa. Many of the Home Savings buildings are now owned by Chase bank. </p>
               </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="9">
                  <head><placeName>Hollywood Palladium, 6215 Sunset Boulevard</placeName> (between Argyle and El Centro)</head>
                  <p>The art deco Hollywood Palladium was built on the site of the original Paramount lot in 1940.  Financed by Los Angeles Times publisher Norman Chandler, it was designed by Gordon Kaufmann, who also designed the Times building and the Hoover Dam.  Frank Sinatra and the Tommy Dorsey Orchestra performed on the ballroom’s opening night on Halloween, 1940, and during World War II it was often used for broadcasts for American troops.  As the big band era falter, the Palladium became home to performances by various Latin music orchestras broadcast by DJ Chico Sesma.  It also served as home to the long-running Lawrence Welk television program.  President Kennedy and Martin Luther King, Jr. both spoke at the Palladium.  Pop Expo ’69 brought Jimi Hendrix to the Palladium and, in the 1980s and 90s, it served as a venue for punk rock, rap, and heavy metal concerts.  The Palladium underwent massive renovations in 2007-08 and Jay-Z performed at the grand re-opening.  In 2012, the Palladium was put up for sale as a development opportunity at an estimated selling price of $60 million. <figure> <graphic url="ssdfasd">
                  </graphic><p>Opening Night, Hollywood Palladium, Oct. 31, 1940
                     "The Hollywood Palladium is for Sale," Pop &amp; Hiss: The L.A. Times Music Blog (5 June 2012)
                     http://latimesblogs.latimes.com/music_blog/2012/06/the-hollywood-palladium-is-for-sale.html</p>
                  </figure></p>
                  
               </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="10">
                  <head><placeName>Hollywood Studio Club, 1215 Lodi Place</placeName> (corner of Lodi and Lexington, just south of Fountain between El Centro and Gower)</head>
                  <p>The Hollywood Studio Club began in 1916 when a group of young women began meeting in the basement of the Hollywood Public Library to read plays.  Thinking they needed a place to meet and study, librarian Eleanor Jones went to the Hollywood YWCA to find a place for them.  Supported by Hollywood businessmen and the movie industry, its original clubhouse was in an old home in Hollywood.  Hollywood scandals in the early 1920s, however, led to tighter controls on the movie industry and, locally, greater oversight over the female Hollywood extra, the “Studio Girl.”   One result was a campaign to build a new Hollywood Studio Club that could house 100 of these young women.  Noted architect Julia Morgan was hired and, in May 1926, the $250,000 building was opened at a gathering of more than 2,500 people including Hollywood celebrities, many of whom had contributed to the building.  Operated by the YWCA, the building was open to any woman seeking jobs such as actress, singer, dancer, script girl, writer, or designer.  Through the 1950s, thousands of women lived there, including some who went on to be Hollywood stars.  By the 1960s, social practices such as the chaperones who looked after the residents seemed obsolete.  Unable to fill its beds, the YWCA opened its doors to transient women regardless of their employment status or aspirations.  In 1975, it closed its door.  The building was name a Los Angeles Historic-Cultural monument in 1977 and placed on the National Register of Historic Places in 1980. </p>
               </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="11">
                  <head><placeName>CBS Columbia Square, 6121 Sunset Boulevard</placeName></head>
                  <p>From 1938 through 2007, CBS Columbia Square was home to the Columbia Broadcasting System’s (CBS) radio and television operations in Los Angeles. Built on the site of Nestor and, subsequently, Christie Studios, it initially housed KNX radio and CBS’s west coast operations.  Designed by Swiss-born William Lescaze, it cost more than $2,000,000 ($30,622,000 in 2010 dollars) and was, in 1938, the most expensive broadcasting studio ever built.  The pilot for I Love Lucy was filmed at Columbia Square in the early days of television and, as the music and movie industries became more closely entwined in the sixties, many of Columbia Records top performers recorded there.  Several plans for redevelopment of the property floundered after 2007.  In 2010, the Los Angeles City Council approved a plan, over some community protest, for a 28-story residential building, a 7-story hotel, and a 17-story office tower.  A 15-year development agreement for the project was approved in March 2011.</p>
                  <p>Listen to an excerpt from the last KNX broadcast from Columbia Square before it moved to new studios on Wilshire Boulevard at http://blog.linder.com/knx/KNX.mp3</p>
               </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="12">
                  <head>Gower Gulch, the corner of Gower and Sunset</head>
                  <p>In the early Hollywood decades, Gower Gulch served as site for cowboy actors and extras to socialize and seek film roles in the movies including those of Universal Film Company, which established a large film lot across from Gower Gulch. During the height of Hollywood production of Westerns in the 1930s and 1940s, services available included saddle and boot repair and sales, as well as a haberdashery for cowboy hats as well as the upscale clothing that cowboy actors came to favor. Both the Gulch and the Studios remain at the intersection today, although in restored forms. Gower Gulch stores of today retain a western theme, but offer a more modern selection of items for sale, including lattes at the Gower Gulch Starbucks. </p>
               </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="13">
                  <head><placeName>Sunset Gower Studios, Sunset Bronson Studios, south side of Sunset between Gower and Bronson</placeName></head>
                  <p>Some of the most famous names in film history had ties to the locations now occupied by the Sunset Gower and Sunset Bronson Studios.  Sam and Jack Warner bought a farm on Sunset between Bronson and Van Ness in 1919.  In 1927, the first talkie, the Jazz Singer, helped them make film history.  Harry Cohn leased a lot at 6070 Sunset, just east of Gower, in 1922 and initially produced many low-budget films that helped earn the area its nickname of “Poverty Row.”  Two years later, he refocused his energies and the result was Columbia Pictures.  Warner eventually moved most of its operations to Burbank, and Sunset Bronson was purchased by Paramount.  Columbia expanded its operations in the area (see Columbia Square), but its connection with Sunset Gower evaporated with Cohn’s death.  Gene Autry purchased Sunset Bronson in 1964 and used it for television production.  The new owners of Sunset Gower diversified to offer music rehearsal spaces and production facilities.  Today, both studios rent their studios and production facilities.  If you pass Sunset Gower at the right time, you will see lines of costumed people waiting for their chance to be on Let’s Make a Deal which is filmed there.</p>
                  
               </div>
               
               <div type="item" n="14">
                  <head><placeName>St. Andrews Bungalow Court, 1514-1544 N. St. Andrews Place</placeName></head>
                  <p>Just a half block north of Sunset on St. Andrew’s place is an early (1919) bungalow court that is particularly well-preserved.  The court appears both on the list of Los Angeles Historic-Cultural Monuments and on the National Register of Historic Places.   Bungalow Courts typically feature multiple small single-family dwellings centered around a central courtyard. The style that emerged in the early 20th century became popular in Hollywood. Originally envisioned as temporary homes for warm weather seeking tourists, they soon came to provide more practical housing, first for temporary residents, and later as permanent, less dense alternatives to apartment buildings in areas with frequent population turnover. Reflecting the aesthetic of the 1920s era when many were built, many have a somewhat simplified Spanish Colonial Revival style with stucco walls and terracotta tile roofs. Other, more elegant bungalow courts were also built and housed some of Hollywood’s glitterati during the “Golden Years.”</p>
               </div>
               
               
            </div>
            
            <div type="subsection">
               <head>Walks Worth Taking</head>
               
               <div type="subsubsection">
                  <head>An indirect walk from Sunset/Highland to Sunset/Vine</head>
                  <p>If you elect to disembark for this stop, you’ll take an approximately one mile long walking tour of part of Hollywood. Get off of the bus at the corner of Sunset and Highland, and walk on the north side of the street. On the northwest corner is Hollywood High School. Walk north on Highland for a few yards and look at the buildings. Continue down Sunset to the east towards Vine. As you walk, observe the people and the environment. What time of day is it and what are the people you see doing? Working? Shopping? What kinds of businesses are here? Identify some of the traces of previous uses of the buildings you see, like deteriorating signs or old cornerstones. Look for signs of the movie industry’s presences as well as other important kinds of business in Hollywood. At the corner of Sunset and Cherokee is the Catholic Church of the Blessed Sacrament and affiliated school. Cross the street and walk south down Cherokee to DeLongpre. </p>
                  
                  <p>The park at Cherokee and DeLongpre is a “pocket park” that was rehabilitated as part of an effort in 2010-2011 to increase green space in LA. In this area, architectural remnants of the movie industry endure. As you are walking, you may notice Bungalow Court style housing, a form that sprang up in Hollywood as the movie industry drew large numbers of workers during the 1920s and 1930s. Additionally, the neighborhood around DeLongpre Park provides a glimpse of some Craftsman style homes, although the grandest in the area is Hollyhock House in Barnsdall Art Park in East Hollywood. When you are finished walking in the park area, take Seward Street north back to Sunset. Walk along Sunset towards Vine, or walk up another block to Hollywood Boulevard for another perspective. From Sunset and Vine, you can see evidence of Hollywood’s past at the Home Savings Bank (now Chase Bank) building as well as evidence of redevelopment efforts over the decades, from the Walk of Fame to the high rise buildings with hip, recently opened eateries on their ground levels. Get something to eat if you like, then reboard the bus.</p>
                  
               </div>
               
               <div type="subsubsection">
                  <head>Second Stop (Hollywood to East Hollywood):</head>
                  <p>Get off the bus at Sunset and Van Ness, cross to the north side of the street. Walk across the bridge over the Hollywood Freeway and look north up the Cahuenga Pass. As you cross, do you see signs of a border or a boundary along Sunset here? What is similar (and what is different) if you compare Sunset west of the freeway to the area east? After you cross the freeway, cross to the south side of the street again (or, if you want to see the bungalow court on St. Andrews Place, stay on the north side and take a brief detour for a block to see it).   Continue walking east on Sunset.  As you walk past the Home Depot on the south side of the street at 5600 Sunset notice whether there are workers they waiting to find work.  Continue until you get to Western Ave. </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            
         </div>
         <!-- closes article div -->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
